现在是 2026 年，给 AI 模型写提示词已经和……大不相同
It is now 2026 and prompting AI models is very different from
2022 年 ChatGPT 刚问世时的情况。
when ChatGPT first came out in 2022.
好好使用 AI 是你能培养的最重要技能之一。
Using AI well is one of the most impactful skills you can develop.
而那些还没有站在 AI 使用前沿的人，常常会遇到 AI
And people that are not yet at the cutting edge of AI usage often run into AI
生成令人沮丧的输出。
generating frustrating outputs.
我希望确保你成为提示词高手
I want to make sure you're an expert prompter
并能充分利用今天的 AI 工具，
and can take advantage of today's AI tools,
这些工具比一年前还要强大得多。
which are much more powerful than they were even a year ago.
我们来看两种不同的体验：AI 新手和 AI 高效使用者。
Let's take a look at two different experiences, the AI novice and the AI power user.
许多 AI 专家已经学会用它回答困难的问题。
Many AI experts have learned to use it to answer hard questions.
相比之下，许多人，包括 AI 新手，
In contrast, many people, including AI novices,
可能已经习惯把 AI 用于简单问题，就像给它输入提示词，
may have gotten used to using AI for simple questions, as if you were prompting it,
就像进行 Google 搜索一样。
like a Google search.
于是你问它：Taco Bell 还有 Double Decker Taco 吗？
So you ask it, does Taco Bell still have the double decker taco?
也许你会得到类似这样的回答，这没问题。
And maybe you get an answer like that, which is fine.
但如果你有更难的问题，
But if you have much harder questions,
你也可以向 AI 提出，并给它时间思考。
you can also ask it of the AI and give it time to think.
例如，如果你打算买一辆车，
For example, if you're looking to buy a car,
你可以向大多数商业服务上传，比如 ChatGPT、Gemini、
you can upload to most of the commercial services, like ChatGPT, Gemini,
Anthropic Claude 或其他服务，上传一组文档，包括汽车规格、报价单、
Anthropic Claude or others, a set of documents including car specs, quotes,
保险计划，然后问它：我正在考虑的这几款车各有什么权衡取舍？
insurance plans, and ask it, what are the trade-offs for these different cars I'm thinking about?
并告诉它要真正思考，在回答前认真想清楚。
And tell it to really think and to think hard before answering.
这会让 AI 花上很多秒甚至几分钟来思考，
And this can cause AI to spend many seconds or even minutes to think
然后为你整理一份详细报告。
and then compile a detailed report for you.
我发现这在我需要做的很多事情上都能节省大量时间。
I find this a huge time saver for a lot of things I have to do.
另一个例子是，AI 高效使用者已经学会提供正确的上下文或
Another example, AI power users have learned to provide the right context or the
正确的背景信息给 AI，让它能够成功回答你的问题。
right background information to the AI to set it up for successfully answering your question.
相比之下，我看到一些 AI 新手只给出很短的提示词，
In contrast, I see some AI novices use a short prompt
然后希望 AI 自己填补空白。
and hope the AI will fill in the blanks.
但如果你把 AI 想成类似于一个非常聪明、刚毕业的大学生，
But if you think of AI as maybe being akin to a really smart, fresh college grad,
积极性很高，但还不太了解你。
highly motivated, but that doesn't really know that much about you yet.
那么一个简短的提示词有时候无法给它足够的信息或
Then a short prompt sometimes doesn't give it enough information or enough
足够的背景上下文来准确回答你的问题。
background context to answer your question accurately.
所以，如果你对 AI 说：请写一份好的自我评价发给我的老板，
So if you tell AI, please write a good self-review to send to my boss,
AI 不知道你在过去一年里实际做了什么，
the AI doesn't know what you've actually done over the last year
因为你还没有告诉它。
because you haven't told it yet.
它可能会写出一份非常笼统的自我评价，没什么帮助。
And it might write a very generic self-review, which isn't that helpful.
相比之下，我发现 AI 高效使用者几乎会站在 AI 的角度思考。
In contrast, I find that AI power users almost have empathy for the AI.
我不想过度拟人化 AI，
I don't want to overly anthropomorphize the AI,
但如果你能设身处地想想一个接收你指令的人，
but if you could put yourself in the shoes of someone getting a set of instructions
你可以问问自己：
from you, you can ask yourself,
他们是否真的足够了解你，能把你交给他们的任务做好？
Will they actually know enough about you to do a good job on the task you're assigning them?
相比之下，AI 高效使用者可能会向 AI 上传大量信息，
So an AI power user, in comparison, might upload a lot of information to the AI,
也许给它一张项目跟踪表的截图，显示你做了哪些工作，
maybe give it a screenshot of a project tracker showing what you worked on,
最近的项目文档，也许是你讲解项目的语音备忘录笔记，
recent project docs, maybe voice memo notes where you talk through the projects
然后让它写一份自我评价发给我的老板。
and then tell it to write a self-review to send to my boss.
这样它就能更好地
And that could do a much better
捕捉你最引以为豪的内容。
job capturing what you're most proud of.
高效使用者学会的一件事，是如何通过提示让 AI 给出真实坦诚的反馈。
One of the things power users have learned to do is how to prompt AI to get honest feedback.
AI 的一个大问题是它常常想讨好你。
A big problem with AI is it often wants to please you.
事实上，许多 AI 系统被训练成尽量让用户满意。
In fact, many AI systems were trained to try to make their users happy.
如果你问它一个带有偏见的问题，
And if you ask it a biased question,
它通常会给出有偏见的回答，
it will often give a biased answer
因为它试图告诉你它认为你想听的话。
because it's trying to tell you what it thinks you want to hear.
例如，如果你说：我有一个很棒的商业点子，移动扎染，
For example, if you say, I have a great business idea, mobile tie-dyeing,
让它给出批判性反馈，但因为你把这说成是很棒的商业点子，
critique it because you called it a great business idea
而且你说这是你的想法。
and you're saying it's your idea.
AI 自然会想讨好你，说这是个多棒的点子。
The AI will naturally want to please you and say what a great idea.
我们有时把这称为迎合倾向。
We sometimes call this sycophancy.
众所周知，如果你哪怕只给出一点点你希望得到什么答案的暗示，
And it's well known that if you give even a hint of what answer you're hoping for,
AI 很可能只是反映出你的偏好或先入之见。
there's a good chance the AI will just reflect back your preferences or your preconceptions.
相比之下，AI 高效使用者往往会提出中立的问题
In contrast, AI power users tend to ask neutral questions
这些问题不会给 AI 任何暗示，让它知道你希望或不希望得到什么答案
that don't give any hint to the AI for what answer you're hoping for or not hoping
或者，如果你给它一个评分标准或评价标准，告诉 AI 如何形成
for, or if you give it a rubric or grading criteria to tell the AI how to form the
它回答的依据。
basis for its answer.
这也会迫使它更加客观。
That also forces it to be more objective.
例如，如果你这样说：
For example, if you were to say,
请客观分析以下商业创意：移动扎染，
please analyze the following business idea objectively, mobile tie-dyeing,
不要只是凭你的猜测编造一堆内容。
and don't just make up a bunch of things for what you think.
请使用上面的评分标准，比如：是否存在问题？
Use the rubric or the grading criteria above, such as is there a problem?
是否有市场？我是否有竞争优势？
Is there a market? Do I have a competitive advantage?
如果你给 AI 这样的指令，那么 AI 就不知道
If you give instructions like this to the AI, then the AI doesn't know.
你是希望它告诉你这是个好主意，还是
Are you hoping it'll tell you it's a great idea or
希望它帮你避免在一个糟糕的商业创意上浪费大量时间。
that it will save you from spending a lot of time on a bad business idea.
这样它就更有可能告诉你类似这样的内容，比如，
And it's much more likely to then tell you something like, oh,
这个创意在 100 分里只能得 8 分。
this idea is an 8 out of 100.
还会解释为什么这个分数很低，万一你真的经营移动扎染业务，
And also why this score's low in case you run a mobile tie-dye business,
我真心祝你好运。
I wish you really the best of luck.
AI 还可以帮助提出一些有用的问题，帮助你思考如何
And AI could also help ask some useful questions to help you think through how to
让这个业务变得更好。
make the business even better.
最后，我发现 AI 新手和 AI 高效使用者让 AI 写作的方式非常不同。
Lastly, I found that AI novices and AI power users ask AI to write in very different ways.
新手只会让 AI 写点东西，比如写一篇关于 Blackberry 的博客文章，
Novices will just ask AI to write stuff like write a blog post about the Blackberry,
它就会生成一堆文字，看起来可能是这样：
and it will generate a bunch of text that maybe looks like this,
听起来就像 AI 垃圾内容。
which sounds like AI slop.
它是一堆泛泛而谈的文字，没什么意思，
It's a bunch of generic text that's just not that interesting
而且占据大量篇幅。
and takes up a lot of space.
相比之下，AI 高效使用者通常不会让 AI 系统直接开始
In contrast, an AI power user will often not ask the AI system to just jump in
写作，而是先让 AI 列出文章大纲
writing directly, but instead ask AI to first outline an article
然后让 AI 对大纲给出批判性反馈，也许还会反复修改几次大纲，以
and then critique the outline and maybe iterate a few times with the outline to
塑造文章，只有到那时才让 AI 开始起草
shape the article and only then ask AI to start to draft
最终文章。
the final article.
因此，在给定一组上传笔记作为上下文的情况下，专家可能会说：
So given a set of uploaded notes as context, an expert may say,
根据我的笔记，列出关于 Blackberry 的博客文章大纲
outline a blog post about the Blackberry based on my notes
这样它就知道你想谈什么。
so it knows what you want to talk about.
AI 可能会先给一个大纲
And the AI may start by giving an outline
然后你可以向 AI 反馈你喜欢哪些地方
and you might then give feedback to the AI about what you like
以及不喜欢大纲的哪些地方。
and what you don't like about the outline.
甚至可以反复几次，进行几个来回
And even iterate a few times, have a few back and forth rounds
直到你得到一个满意的大纲
before you have an outline that you're satisfied with
也许会到那时才把大纲扩展成要点，甚至可能再回头
and maybe only then expand the outline into bullet points and maybe even go back
来回几次，让 AI 针对要点给出批判性反馈，直到你满意
and forth a few times to critique the bullet points before you're satisfied with
然后再把它扩展成最终文本。
that and then expand it into the final text.
这种高效使用者工作流更有可能生成一些文本
This type of power user workflow is much more likely to generate some text
让你满意，而不是 AI 垃圾内容。
that you're happy with as opposed to AI slop.
而在这类工作流中，你把 AI
And in this type of workflow, you're treating the AI
当作思考伙伴，让它帮助你进行头脑风暴
as a thinking partner to almost help you brainstorm
并探索你可能想写的不同选项。
and explore different options for what you might want to write.
AI 系统确实会犯错，但可能比大多数人以为的要少，
AI systems do make mistakes, but maybe fewer than most people think,
尤其是当你给出好的提示词时。
especially if you prompt it well.
它们在 2022 年或 2023 年犯的错比现在多得多，
They made a lot more mistakes back in 2022 or 2023 than they do now,
但很多被广泛传播的 AI 错误，
but a lot of widely publicized mistakes that AI has made,
其中一些在社交媒体上疯传，
some of which went viral on social media.
让人们以为 AI 犯的错误可能比实际更多。
Have made people think that AI maybe makes even more mistakes than it actually does.
有一个广为人知的例子，人们问它：
There's a well-publicized one where people asked it,
strawberry 这个单词里有多少个 R？
how many R's are there in the word strawberry?
它以为有两个 R。
And it thinks there are two R's.
还有一个我觉得很有趣的例子：我想洗车，
And here's one that I found amusing. I want to wash my car.
我应该走路还是开车去？AI 说走路，这要么会让你人到了那里，
Should I walk or drive there? And AI says walk, which would leave you there,
要么洗你的车。
or wash your car.
但这些疯传的例子并不能代表 AI 的能力。
But these viral examples are not representative of AI capabilities.
相比之下，AI 高效使用者知道，AI 能通过一些任务带来巨大价值，比如
In contrast, power users know that AI can deliver significant value through tasks like
进行深度研究并撰写研究报告，或者把你的个人数据，
doing deep research and writing research reports or taking your personal data,
比如健康、心率或跑步时间数据，拿来为你分析，
like your health or heart rate or running time data and analyzing that for you,
或者我们稍后会讲到的，甚至构建网站。
or something we'll talk about later. Even building websites.
为你构建网站。
for you.
我见过成为 AI 高效使用者给个人带来巨大益处，同时
I've seen being an AI power user tremendously benefit individuals as well
也给他们的企业带来巨大益处。
as their businesses.
它会帮你节省时间，并改善你的职业和个人生活。
It'll save you time and improve your professional and personal lives.
它会帮你构建很多很酷的东西。
It'll help you to build lots of cool things.
在后面的视频中，你会学到怎么做。
You'll learn how later in these videos.
能够以专家水平给 AI 写提示，是一项非常抢手的工作技能，无论
and being able to prompt AI at an expert level is a highly in-demand job skill no
你从事什么职位。
matter what job role you're in.
在接下来的视频中，我希望带你从今天的水平出发，成为
In the rest of these videos, I hope to take you from wherever you are today to being
一名 AI 高效使用者。
an AI power user.
关于 AI 很有用，已经有很多讨论。
Much has been said about AI being useful.
我还觉得使用 AI 真的很有趣。
I find using AI really fun as well.
在这些视频中你也会看到一些例子。
And you'll see a few examples of that in these videos too.
现在，一个非常基础的知识点
Now, one foundational piece of knowledge
能帮助你更好地使用 AI，就是理解它的知识从何而来，这样
that helps you work with AI is understanding where it gets its knowledge from so
你就能更好地预判什么时候它会给出正确答案，
that you can better predict when you'll get something right and
以及什么时候你或许不该
when you maybe shouldn't.
依赖这个答案。
count on this answer.
让我们进入下一个视频，了解 AI 是如何获取知识的。
Let's go on to the next video to learn about how AI gets its knowledge.
你小时候是怎么学会写作的？
How did you learn to write as a child?
很可能涉及大量阅读。嗯，AI 也是一样。
Probably it involved reading a lot of things. Well, it's the same for AI.
AI 系统通过阅读互联网上的大量文本学会了各种模式。
AI systems have learned patterns from reading large amounts of text from the internet.
通过了解 AI 所读文本中的内容，
By understanding what's in that text the AI has read,
你就能更好地预测它们的行为方式。
you'd be better able to predict how they'll behave.
AI 模型可以回答各种主题的问题，比如你问，
AI models can answer questions on a variety of topics if you were to ask,
“我把手机掉进汤里了。
I dropped my phone in soup.
我该怎么办？”希望它会给出一些有用的建议。
What shall I do then? Hopefully it'll make some useful suggestions.
或者“为什么猫盯着墙看，就像看到了鬼一样？”
Or why do cats stare at walls like they're seeing ghosts?
我女儿很喜欢猫。她确实对这个问题很好奇。
My daughter loves cats. She was actually curious about this.
事实证明，猫能察觉到一些细微的声音和动作，而我们
Turns out cats can detect subtle sounds and movements that we
作为人类常常会忽略。由于 AI 在互联网上阅读了大量内容，
as humans often miss. Because of the amount of things it read on the internet,
它们甚至会掌握一些很少有人知道的小众知识。
they will even possess niche knowledge that few people know about.
如果你问，多年前被送入太空的黑胶唱片上有什么内容，
If you ask what kind of things were on the vinyl record sent into space years ago,
NASA 有一艘名为 Voyager 1 的航天器，于 20 世纪 70 年代发射，
NASA had a spacecraft called Voyager 1 that launched in the 1970s
现在距离地球约 250 亿英里。
and is now about 25 billion miles away from Earth.
但 AI 会知道这些，并能够告诉你那张黑胶唱片上有什么。
But AI will know about this and be able to tell you what is on that vinyl record.
我觉得很酷的是，NASA 选择用 55 种不同的语言发送问候，
I think it's cool that NASA chose to send greetings in 55 different languages to
给任何可能遇到那艘太空探测器的人，如果真的有人会遇到。
whoever may come across that space probe, if anyone does.
AI 模型在非常非常多不同的信息来源上进行训练，
AI models are trained on many, many different sources of information,
主要来自互联网。而在所有这些非常多样化的知识来源上进行训练，
mainly from the internet and training on all of these very diverse sources of
就产生了它的预训练知识。
knowledge produces its pre-trained knowledge.
预训练（pre-trained）是一个技术术语，你不必担心。
The term pre-trained is a technical term that you don't have to worry about.
实际上，AI 系统是分多个步骤训练的，
It turns out AI systems are trained in multiple steps,
而这是训练的最初步骤之一，
and this is one of the first steps of training
不知怎么就被称为预训练（pre-training），这不是一个很好的术语，
that somehow wound up being called pre-training, which isn't a great term,
但我不会纠结为什么叫它预训练。
but I wouldn't worry about why we call it pre-training.
它就是 AI 所学内容的来源。
It's just what AI has learned from.
但这些知识来源可能包括来自 Reddit 等社交媒体的大量文本，
But these knowledge sources may include a lot of text from social media like Reddit,
里面有“你必看的电影有哪些？”这类问题的答案。
which have answers to questions like, what are your must-watch films?
或者它可能读过关于 Lego 微型城市的书，或读过 Wikipedia 上关于仙女面包的文章，
Or it may have read a book on Lego micro cities or read a Wikipedia article on fairy
以及很多其他内容，
bread and lots of other things,
也可能读了很多新闻文章，
or read a bunch of news articles as well
以及阅读了大量互联网上的研究文章。
as read a lot of research articles on the internet.
互联网论坛和 Reddit、Quora 等社交媒体上有大量文本。
There's a lot of text on internet forums and social media like Reddit and Quora.
AI 会读很多书。
There are a lot of books that AI will have read.
还有像 Wikipedia 这样的百科全书、新闻网站，
There are encyclopedias like Wikipedia, news websites,
研究文章等等。
research articles and much more.
因此，这些数万亿乃至数十万亿的词语会用于训练 AI 模型的大脑。
And so these trillions or tens of trillions of words will go into training the AI model's brain.
现在，不同类型的数据在互联网上出现的频率各不相同。
Now, different types of data appear with different amounts of frequency on the internet.
因此，这些预训练知识反映了训练数据中的频率或模式。
And so this pre-trained knowledge reflects the frequency or the patterns in the training data.
例如，烹饪是一种非常普遍的人类体验，
For example, cooking is a very universal human experience,
所以互联网上有大量关于烹饪的文章。
so there are a lot of articles on the internet on cooking.
网上也有很多关于名人、电影的文章。
There are also a lot of articles online on celebrities, on movies.
因此，AI 会看过很多关于这些主题的文本。
And so AI will have seen a lot of text on these topics.
相比之下，还有一些更专业的主题，比如类星体，
In contrast, there are more specialized topics like quasars,
这是一个天文学术语，指天空中非常明亮的天体，它们由
which is an astronomical term referring to really bright objects in the sky powered
超大质量黑洞驱动。
by supermassive black holes.
我觉得它们很迷人，但关于类星体的文章比
I think they're fascinating, but there are just a lot fewer articles on quasars than
互联网上关于烹饪的文章要少得多。如今，虽然互联网大部分内容都是英文，
on cooking on the internet. Now, while most of the internet is in English,
AI 系统也会从一些其他语言写成的数据中学习。
AI systems will also have learned from some data that's written in other languages.
比如粤语。
Like Cantonese.
超过 8000 万人说粤语，但远少于说英语的人。
Over 80 million people speak Cantonese, but that's far less than English.
而粤语数据可能只占所有互联网内容的不到 0.1%。
And Cantonese data represents maybe less than 0.1% of all internet content.
最后，还有一些 AI 模型完全不知道的事情，
Lastly, there are things that AI models know nothing about at all,
比如你公司的秘密专有数据，
such as your company's secret proprietary data,
希望这些数据不在公开互联网上，
which hopefully is not on the open internet,
但因此 AI 系统也不会从这些数据中学习。
but which an AI system will therefore not have learned from.
所以我觉得，思考数据在互联网上出现的频率有多高，能给你一个
So I find that thinking about how frequent data appears on the internet gives you a
很好的经验法则，用来判断 AI 系统回答的可靠性。
good rule of thumb for thinking about how reliable an AI system's responses are.
现在，由于 AI 从这些数据中学习，
Now, because of the data the AI has learned from,
它有时会表现出对事物令人惊讶的理解。
sometimes it can exhibit surprising understanding of things.
如果你打字很快，
If you were to type very quickly,
像左边展示的“能用微波炉煮鸡蛋吗？”
can you cook eggs in microwave as shown on the left?
它实际上能很好地理解这类拼写错误的文本，
It can actually understand this type of misspelled text very well,
几乎和询问“能用微波炉煮鸡蛋吗？”一样好。
pretty much as well as asking, can you cook eggs in the microwave?
顺便说一句，我自己就在微波炉里炸过几个鸡蛋。
And by the way, I've exploded a few eggs in the microwave myself.
所以如果你想避免这种情况，可以随时问 AI 系统该怎么做，
So if you ever want to avoid that, feel free to ask the AI system how to do so,
这样你就不必通过惨痛教训来学习。
so you don't have to learn the hard way.
它之所以这么擅长理解拼写错误的词语，是因为
And a reason that it's so good at understanding misspelled words is
它实际上学习了很多可能包含错别字的来源。
because it's actually learned from a lot of sources that could include typos.
所以如果你上网看，你会看到很多拼写错误的短语。
So if you look online, you will see phrases misspelled.
这就是为什么当你使用 AI 系统时，
And that's why when you're using the AI system,
我并不是鼓励你使用糟糕的语法或拼错单词。
I'm not encouraging you to use bad grammar or to misspell words.
但事实证明，如果你打字很快，
But it turns out that if you're typing quickly
而且你有一些错别字，甚至很多错别字，也不用太担心。
and you have a few typos or even a lot of typos, don't worry too much about it.
直接向 AI 发送提示词是完全可以的，
It's pretty fine to just send a prompt to AI
不必花太多时间去修正每一个小的语法错误。
and not spend too much time fixing every little grammatical error.
但坏消息是，AI 的很多知识来源也包含误解
Now, the bad news is a lot of AI sources also have misconceptions
和过时的信息。
and outdated information.
所以使用 AI 的技能之一，就是如何给它提示词，让它返回
So one of the skills in using AI is how to prompt it to have it give you back
反映更少误解的答案，
answers that reflect fewer misconceptions
并且不会过度反映过时的信息。
and does not overly reflect outdated information.
通过了解 AI 的知识来源，也就是预训练知识，
By understanding AI's knowledge sources, called pretrained knowledge,
你就能更好地预测它会如何响应你的提示词。
you'll be able to better predict how it will respond to your prompts.
但这种预训练知识并不足以应对所有应用场景，
But this pretrained knowledge is not enough for all applications,
包括那些需要实时信息的场景。
including those that need real-time information.
为此，你需要联网搜索。让我们进入下一个视频，了解更多。
For that, you need to web search. Let's go on to the next video to learn more.
在某个时间点，构建 AI 模型的人不得不停止训练它。
At some point, the people building the AI model had to stop its training.
所以会有一个最后日期，它的信息在此截止。
So there's some last date where its information cuts off.
AI 只读到某个特定日期和时间之前的互联网内容，
The AI has read the internet only up to a certain date and time
它的知识也在那个日期被冻结在了时间里。
and its knowledge gets frozen in time as of that date.
但当然，世界过了那个日期仍在继续前进。
But of course, the world moves on past that date.
新的事情发生，电影上映等等。
New things happen, movies come out and so on.
让我们看看 AI 模型如何通过联网搜索获取新信息，以便
Let's see how AI models handle gathering new information using web search so
它能够回答一些问题，
that it can address questions
甚至涉及知识截止日期之后的事情。
that even relate to things after its knowledge cutoff date
如果你正在使用某个主流 AI 模型提供商，比如 ChatGPT，
if you're using one of the popular AI model providers like ChatGPT,
Gemini 和 Claude，那么有些问题
Gemini and Claude, there are certain questions
很可能会触发它进行联网搜索。
that will probably trigger it to do a web search.
例如，如果你问它 2025 年的 6, 7 梗是什么？
For example, if you ask it what is the 6, 7 meme from 2025?
它很可能会在互联网上搜索，然后告诉你 6, 7 梗
There's a good chance it will search on the internet to tell you that the 6, 7 meme,
读作 six seven，这个读音说起来挺有趣
which is pronounced six seven, which is just kind of fun to say
这是一个在多个社交媒体平台上广泛传播的网络热梗。
that this is a viral internet slang widely seen on a few social media platforms.
它触发搜索的原因是
And the reason it triggers
当你问它“2025 年的 6, 7 梗是什么”时，它会进行联网搜索。
a web search when you ask it, what's a 6, 7 meme from 2025?
其中的“2025”会让 AI 意识到，它可能需要更多更新的在线
The 2025 causes AI to realize that it may benefit from more updated online
信息，因为这可能是一个出现在互联网上的梗
information because this could be a meme that appeared on the internet
而且是在它的知识截止日期之后。
after its knowledge cutoff date.
我解释一下。
Here's what I mean.
一个特定 AI 模型的预训练知识在时间上是冻结的，
A specific AI model's pretrained knowledge is frozen in time,
尽管互联网会随着时间不断演化。
even though the internet continues to evolve over time.
所以如果这条线代表时间，
And so if this line represents time,
那么在很长一段时间里，互联网上都会有写着 6 × 7 = 42 的文本。
then for a long time the internet will have had pieces of text that say 6 × 7 = 42.
还有关于那个儿童笑话的文本：为什么 6 害怕 7？
Text that talks about the children's joke. Why was 6 afraid of 7?
因为 7、8、9。
Because 7, 8, 9.
但如果知识截止日期在某个时间点，而 6、
But if the knowledge cutoff date was at a certain moment in time and the 6,
7 梗是在那之后才出现的。
7 meme came after that.
那么这个 6, 7 梗就不会出现在 AI 模型的预训练知识中。
Then the 6, 7 meme will not have been seen in the pretrained knowledge of the AI model.
所以如果你问它“2025 年的 6, 7 梗是什么”，
So if you ask it, what is the 6, 7 meme from 2025,
AI 模型会意识到自己不知道这个 6、
the AI model will realize that it doesn't know about this 6,
7 梗是 2025 年的，并且它应该进行联网搜索，以获取更新的信息。
7 meme from 2025 and that it should do a web search in order to get more updated information.
以 OpenAI 的 GPT 5.4 模型为例，它的知识截止日期是 2025 年 8 月。
Take the GPT 5.4 model from OpenAI, its knowledge cutoff date was August 2025.
这张图显示了 Google 上搜索“6, 7 是什么意思”的次数。
And this graph shows how many Google web searches there were for what does 6, 7 mean.
所以这个 6, 7 梗是在 GPT 5.4 的知识截止日期之后才流行起来的，
So this 6, 7 meme had taken off after this GPT 5.4 knowledge cutoff date,
这就是为什么该模型不太了解这个梗。
which is why the model doesn't really know about this meme.
现在，有些类型的问题
Now, there are certain types of questions
AI 会用它的预训练知识来回答，
that an AI will answer using its pretrained knowledge,
而有些类型的问题则倾向于触发联网搜索。
and there are certain types of questions that will tend to trigger web search.
例如，如果你告诉它：请帮我在 Mountain View 附近找一家评分很高的健身房，
For example, if you tell it, please find me a highly rated gym near Mountain View,
加州，那么什么是“评分很高”？
California, then what is highly rated?
哪些开门、哪些关门确实会随时间变化。
What may be open and what may be closed does change over time.
这很可能会触发联网搜索；或者如果你问它，
And there's a good chance that this will trigger a web search or if you ask it,
什么是 Market, Mountain Cheese Roll，
what is the Market, Mountain Cheese Roll,
因为这是一个很小众的信息。
because this is a niche piece of information.
网上关于这个奶酪卷的信息可能不太多。
It's probably not really a lot of information online about this cheese roll.
它很可能会搜索互联网来给你一个答案。
There's a good chance that it will search the internet in order to get you an answer.
如果你好奇的话，这其实是一个非常有趣的活动
And if you're curious, this is actually a pretty fun event
人们追着一个滚下山的奶酪轮跑。
where people chase a rolling wheel of cheese down the hill.
让我们更广泛地看看
Let's take a look more broadly at
AI 模型在什么情况下需要进行联网搜索来收集更多信息。
when an AI model needs to do some web search to gather more information.
为了回答你的问题，如果你问的是：
To answer your question, if you're asking what to do
如果你把手机掉进汤里怎么办，或者猫为什么盯着墙看，或者 Voyager
if you drop your phone in soup or why do cats stare at walls or what's on the Voyager
1 号唱片在太空中有什么？
1 record in outer space?
那么这些问题它可能可以用预训练知识来回答
Then these questions it could probably answer using this pretrained knowledge
因为这些都属于互联网上的常识。
because these are represented in common knowledge on the internet.
但如果被问到当前事件或最近才发生的事情，
But if it was asked about current events or something happening very recently,
那么它就需要进行联网搜索来获取实时信息。
then it'll need to do web search to get that real time information.
如果你询问某个特定地点的信息，并且联网搜索是有意义的，或者
If you ask it location specific information and doing a web search makes sense or
如果你询问其他类型的小众信息，
if you ask it for other types of niche information,
它也很可能会意识到自己对那个主题了解不够。
there's also a good chance it'll realize it doesn't know enough about that topic.
进行联网搜索收集更多信息，会帮助它给你更好的答案。
That doing a web search to gather more information would help it give you a better answer.
对于大多数主流 AI 模型提供商来说，
For most of the popular AI model providers,
联网搜索可以通过两种方式触发。
web search can be triggered in either of two ways.
有时 AI 模型会自己决定进行联网搜索，或者你也可以
Sometimes the AI model will decide by itself to carry out the web search or you can also
显式地触发联网搜索，有时可以点击 AI 模型
explicitly trigger web search sometimes by clicking one of the buttons in an AI model
提供商网页界面中的某个按钮，或者直接写提示词。
provider's web interface or just writing your prompt.
请让它对此进行联网搜索，它就会照做。
Please do a web search for this and it will comply
并使用联网搜索来回答你的问题。
and use the web search to answer your question,
并非所有 AI 模型都启用了联网搜索。
not all AI models have web search enabled,
但你可能正在使用的主流模型大多都具备这个能力。
but the most popular ones that you're probably using mostly do have this capability.
AI 会在很多
AI will do better on many of the
你想让它做的任务上表现更好，如果它能联网搜索。
tasks you want to use it for if it does web search
联网搜索能让它用更新的信息补充预训练知识。
and web search allows it to augment its pre-trained knowledge with more current information.
但就像所有联网搜索一样，它也可能返回不可靠的信息来源。
But like all web search, it can return bad sources.
我们来看看这在什么时候会成为问题，以及
Let's take a look at when this is an issue and when
如何让它使用更可靠的来源，给你更可靠的答案。
and how to get it to use more reliable sources to get you more reliable answers.
联网搜索是一个非常有价值但并不完美的工具。
Web search is a very valuable but imperfect tool.
就像你自己上网搜索一样，
Just like when you search the web yourself,
你可能不总能找到你要找的内容。
you might not always find what you're looking for.
它有局限性，比如找到过时或不准确的来源。
It has limitations, like finding old or inaccurate sources.
但你可以绕过这些限制，让 AI 给你更准确、
But you can work around these limitations to get AI to give you more accurate
更新的答案。
and up-to-date answers.
我们来看一下。
Let's take a look.
如果你问一个 AI 系统灰色市场肽类有多安全，
If you ask an AI system how safe are grey market peptides,
这是一种补充剂，它可能会在网上搜索
which is a type of supplement, it may search online
并找到社交媒体上的帖子，或 Reddit、Quora 等公共论坛网站上的帖子。
and find posts on social media or public forum sites like Reddit and Quora.
或者你可能找到以销售肽类产品为业的网站，
Or you may find websites that are in the business of selling peptides and
因此它们倾向于告诉你这些产品是安全的。
so would have an inclination to tell you that they are safe.
你得到的回答可能准确，也可能不准确，
And you may get back answers that may or may not be accurate,
但如果你鼓励 AI 模型使用官方组织的来源，或查看
but if you encourage the AI model to use sources from official organizations or look
有严谨科学支持的研究。
at studies that are backed by rigorous science.
那它更可能去查找来自 World Health Organization（世界卫生组织）、
Then it's more likely to look up resources from the World Health Organization,
US Food and Drug Administration（美国食品药品监督管理局）、
from the US Food and Drug Administration,
European Medicines Agency（欧洲药品管理局）等机构的资源，
from the European Medicines Agency and so on,
从而有望给你更可靠、更具科学可信度的回答。
and hopefully give you more reliable and scientifically credible answers.
无论是人类在 Google 或 Bing 上搜索，还是由 AI 进行的联网搜索，
Web search, whether done by a human on Google or Bing or done by AI,
都倾向于引用流行的来源。
has a tendency to draw from popular sources.
根据一份报告，AI 模型引用最多的网站是 Reddit，
According to one report, the most cited website by AI models was Reddit,
其次是 Wikipedia、YouTube，然后是 Google 本身、Yelp 等。
followed by Wikipedia, YouTube, then Google itself, Yelp and so on.
其中一些来源比其他来源更值得信赖。
And some of these sources are more trustworthy than others.
互联网上来自社交媒体、博客、在线论坛的文本非常多，
There's just a lot of text on the internet from social media, blogs, online forums,
而来自高度可靠、
and the amount of text from highly reliable,
经科学验证来源的文本量则少得多。
scientifically verified sources is just much smaller.
所以如果你不引导模型你偏好哪些类型的来源，
So if you don't steer the model in terms of what types of sources you prefer,
它就有可能会从最容易获取的文本中提取，
there's a chance that it'll tend to pull text from whatever is most available
而不是从最可靠的来源中提取。
rather than what's most reliable.
所以这就是为什么如果你问它“灰色市场肽类有多安全”，
So that's why if you ask it, how safe are grey market peptides,
它可能会把大量回答建立在社交媒体博客和论坛上，
it might base a lot of its answer on social media blogs and forums
只有很少一部分来自更可靠的来源。
and only a little bit on the more reliable sources.
而如果你告诉它使用官方卫生组织的来源，
Whereas if you tell it to use sources from official health organizations,
它可能会更多地从这些可靠的信息来源获取信息。
it may pull much more from these reliable sources.
联网搜索的另一个局限是，有时网页可能已经过时。
Another limitation of web search is that sometimes web pages can be outdated.
这可能导致 AI 模型也无法提供最新的信息。
That can lead the AI model to also not provide the most current information.
我们一位朋友的 AI 最近帮我寻找内华达州亨德森适合跑步的地方。
A friend of ours' AI recently helped me find places to run in Henderson, Nevada.
这是一个针对特定地点的细分查询。
This is a location-specific niche query.
于是这触发了联网搜索，它找到了一个适合慢跑的地点清单。
And so this triggers web search and it found this list of places to go for a jog.
但不幸的是，结果发现，
But it turns out that unfortunately,
这些内容来自一个已有二十多年历史的网页。
this pulled from a web page from more than two decades ago.
不幸的是，建议的地点是一所学校，与几十年前不同，
And unfortunately, the location suggested was a school that, unlike decades ago,
这所学校已不再向公众开放供跑步。为了帮助你建立关于
is no longer open to the public to go running in. To help build intuition about how
AI 如何搜索网络并使用这些信息的直觉。
AI searches the web and uses that information.
让我简要解释一下联网搜索实际上是如何在后台运作的。
Let me briefly explain how web search actually works under the hood.
它其实是一个多步骤的过程。
It turns out to be a multi-step process.
想象一下，你正在向一个两人的客服团队提问。
Imagine that you're asking questions of a customer service team of two people.
其中有一个面向用户的 AI 模型，那正是你在交谈的对象。
There's the user-facing AI model. That's what you are talking to.
而面向用户的 AI 模型还有第二个助手 AI 模型。
And the user-facing AI model has a second assistant AI model
它可以请求帮助来进行联网搜索。
that it can ask for help to do web search.
所以当你发送提示词时，你是在与第一个模型对话，
So when you send a prompt, you are talking to the first model,
也就是面向用户的 AI 模型，它偶尔会决定调用
the user-facing AI model, and it will occasionally decide to call up the
辅助 AI 模型，也就是第二个 AI，说：“嘿，
assistant AI model, the second AI, to say, hey.
请帮我执行联网搜索，以收集更多信息。”
Please do a web search for me to gather more information.
这个辅助 AI 模型随后会在一个非常类似于
This assistant AI model will then search on a web search engine very similar to
我们人类可能会使用的 Google、Bing 及其他联网搜索引擎上进行搜索。
Google and Bing and other web search engines that we as people might use.
它会浏览返回的结果，
And it will scan the returned results,
过滤掉不相关的结果，并下载最相关的网页
filter out the irrelevant results and download the most relevant web pages
然后进行总结。
and then summarize them.
然后，第二个辅助 AI 模型会将这些摘要返回给第一个
The second assistant AI model will then present the summaries back to the first
模型，也就是面向用户的 AI 模型。
model, the user-facing AI model.
第一个模型随后会利用这些摘要，为你生成最终回答。
And the first model will then use these summaries in order to generate the final answer for you.
你只在与面向用户的 AI 模型对话。
You are speaking only to the user-facing AI model.
需要记住的一个有趣特点是，面向用户的 AI 模型并没有
And one interesting quirk to keep in mind is the user-facing AI model has not
真正完整读过它可能为你引用的所有网页。相反，
actually read in its entirety all of the web pages it may be citing for you. Instead,
它只看到了那些网页的摘要。
it's only seen summaries of those web pages.
有时这会导致它误解某个被引用的底层网页
And sometimes this causes it to misinterpret what one of these underlying web pages
实际所说的内容，这就是为什么你可能见过一些有趣的结果：
actually says, which is why you may have seen funny results
AI 引用某个网页，并声称该网页证明了某个结论。
where AI cites a web page and says the web page justifies a conclusion.
但如果你自己去看那个网页，
But if you look at that web page yourself,
它实际上并不能证明面向用户的 AI 模型所说的内容。
it doesn't actually justify what the user-facing AI model says it is doing.
为了带你走一遍这个问题流程中的一个例子，
To walk you through one example of this problem process,
如果你问面向用户的 AI 模型，
if you ask the user-facing AI model,
它就像与你对话的客服人员，它会问：
that's like the customer service agent talking to you, it will ask,
“徒步马丘比丘之前，我应该了解什么？”
what should I know before hiking Machu Picchu?
第二个模型可能会用“马丘比丘许可证”之类的短语进行一些联网搜索，
The second model may do some web searches with phrases like Machu Picchu permits,
“马丘比丘天气”或“社会习俗”等等。
Machu Picchu weather or the social customs and so on.
然后它会浏览返回的结果，就像你可能会浏览一页 Google 搜索结果
And it'll then scan the returned results much like you may scan a page of Google
来判断哪些相关、并过滤掉不相关的结果
results to decide what's relevant and filter out irrelevant results
并总结最相关的网页，提供给第一个 agent
and summarize the most relevant web pages to provide back to the first agent
然后由它为你生成最终回答。如今，我经常使用
that then generates the final answer for you. Now, I frequently use.
像 ChatGPT、Gemini 这样的 AI 模型，
AI models like ChatGPT, Gemini,
以及 Claude，我也经常使用像 Google 和 Bing 这样的联网搜索引擎。
Claude and I also frequently use web search engines like Google and Bing.
什么时候应该用 AI 模型，什么时候应该用联网搜索引擎？
When should you use an AI model and when should you use a web search engine?
如果你想快速浏览多个信息来源，搜索引擎会很有用。
If you want to quickly scan multiple sources, a search engine can be useful for that.
或者，如果你想前往某个特定网站
Or if you want to navigate to a specific website
但忘了那个网站的名字？
but have forgotten what's the name of that website?
联网搜索引擎可以很好地帮你找到它，或者
Web search engine can be very good for helping you find it or
如果你想查看原始形式的数据，
if you want to look at data in its original form,
比如你想购买 2013 年 Honda Civic 的空气滤清器。
such as if you want to buy a 2013 Honda Civic air filter.
你懂的，你想找到一个网站去买那个空气滤清器。
You know, you want to find a website to go to to buy that air filter.
所以联网搜索引擎非常擅长这些。
So web search engine is very good at that.
相比之下，如果你想从多个信息来源获得综合总结，或者
In contrast, if you want to get the synthesis from multiple sources or
如果你要搜索更复杂、带有优缺点需要权衡的信息
if you're searching for more complex information with pros and cons
或者你只是想对比多个信息来源，以得出
that you want weighed or if you just want to contrast multiple sources to come up
一个更深思熟虑的结论。
with a more thoughtful conclusion.
那么 AI 模型可以执行联网搜索
Then an AI model can do a web search
并相当高效地为你汇总多个网页的结果，
and put together the results of multiple web pages for you quite efficiently,
从而也许能节省你亲自阅读大量网页的时间。
thus maybe saving you time of having to read a lot of web pages yourself.
你可能已经养成了一些好的 Google 或其他联网搜索习惯
There might be some good Google or other web search habits that you've developed
这些习惯也会让你受益
and those habits will serve you well
当你使用支持联网搜索的 AI 模型时也是如此，
when working with web-search-enabled AI models as well,
比如寻找可靠的信息来源，以及再次核查这些来源。
things like looking for reliable sources and also double-checking the sources.
但如果你想超越仅仅搜索少量网页，
But if you want to go beyond searching a handful of web pages,
事实证明，AI 模型能够进行一种范围更广的研究，称为深度研究。
it turns out AI models are capable of a much more extensive type of research called deep research.
这是一项非常强大的能力，我认为很多人都没有充分利用。
This is a very powerful capability that I think is really underused by many people.
让我们继续观看下一个视频，了解它是什么，以及何时
Let's go on to the next video to see what it is and when
以及如何使用深度研究。
and how to use deep research.
有时你可能希望 AI 不仅综合少量信息来源，而是很多来源，
Sometimes you may want your AI to synthesize not just a handful of sources, but many,
可能会查阅几十个来源，并进行大量思考，以得出最佳
maybe many dozens of sources, and do lots of thinking to come up with the best
为你提出的问题提供经过深度研究的、尽可能好的答案。
possible deeply researched answer to a question that you have.
像 ChatGPT 这样的热门 AI 聊天界面，
Popular AI chat interfaces like ChatGPT,
Gemini 和 Claude 都有深度研究模式。
Gemini and Claude all have a deep research mode.
我发现这是一个非常有价值、却常被低估的工具。
I found this to be a very valuable and often underutilized tool.
我们来看看。
Let's take a look.
假设你想用 AI 模型来帮你规划万圣节鬼屋。
Let's say you want to use an AI model to help you plan your Halloween haunted house.
我会写一条提示词，让它帮我在前院布置一个鬼屋。
I'm gonna write a prompt to ask it to help me set up a haunted house in my front
用于万圣节。
yard for Halloween.
并告诉它一些信息，比如我在哪里、前院有多大，
And give it some information about where I am, what's the size of my front yard,
以及我想要怎样的体验。
what's the experience I want.
所以我给它大量上下文，让它为我做出合适的规划。
So I give it lots of context to set it up, to plan it out for me appropriately.
有了这样的提示词，AI 模型可能会制定一个研究计划，
With a prompt like this, an AI model might come up with a research plan in
它会尝试思考需要研究哪些类型的来源，
which it tries to think through what are the types of sources it needs to research,
许多系统会给你机会批准或编辑这个研究计划。
many systems would give you an opportunity to approve or potentially edit the research plan.
如果你对计划满意，我通常会直接启动而不做修改，
And if you're happy with it, I'll often launch the research plan without updating it
除非我看到某些明显不对的地方。
unless I see something that just looks really wrong.
然后它会开始进行在线搜索。
It will then go ahead and start to do online searches.
这个例子一开始会收集 Palo Alto 的许可规定，
So this example starts by gathering Palo Alto's rules on permits,
万圣节条例等。
Halloween ordinances and so on.
然后它会阅读其中一些网页，并综合已知信息，
And then it will read some of those web pages and synthesize what is learned
然后它可能会决定做更多在线搜索，以收集更多
so far and it may then decide to do some more searches online to gather more
有关消防安全指南的信息。
information about fire safety guidelines.
之后它可能会决定查找装饰创意。
And then it may after that decide to look for decoration ideas.
所以它大致遵循最初的研究计划，
So it loosely follows the original research plan,
但也有灵活性，可以继续深入探究某些方面，
but also has the flexibility to keep looking deeper into certain areas
如果它在搜索一段时间后认为需要这些信息，
if it thinks it needs that information after searching for a while,
也许数分钟后，它最终会为你写一份详细的研究报告。
maybe many minutes, it will finally write a detailed research report for you.
顺便说一下，这个过程是 agentic AI（智能体 AI）的一个例子，它指的是
This process, by the way, is an example of agentic AI and what that refers to is
通过这个深度研究过程，
that through this deep research process,
AI 模型可以自行灵活决定下一步做什么。
the AI model has some flexibility to make decisions by itself on what to do next.
比如是否需要进行额外搜索，以及进行哪些搜索。
Such as what additional searches, if any, to carry out?
这样得到的输出可以是一份相当详细
The output of this can then be a fairly detailed
且考虑周全的计划，分为不同部分，概述你可能需要考虑的
and thoughtful plan with different sections outlining what you might need to think
有关结构和监管框架的内容，
about in terms of structure and regulatory framework,
以及安全等问题，如果你使用 Google 的 Gemini AI 模型。
safety and so on if you're using Google's Gemini AI model for this.
其中一个巧妙的功能是，它可以轻松地将已经完成的深度研究
One of the neat features is it makes it easy to take the deep research it's done
并帮助你把它转换成网页、信息图或其他几种形式。
and helps you turn it into a web page or infographic or handful of other things.
这里有一个网页，是 Gemini 使用 Gemini Deep Research 生成的。
Here's a web page that was generated by Gemini using the Gemini Deep Research.
我觉得它很不错。
And I think it's pretty neat.
它生成了一个包含 4 个部分的网页，包括预算饼图，
This created a web page with 4 different sections, pie charts for budget,
以及关于噪音条例的不错的可视化。
pretty neat visualizations for noise ordinance.
我觉得它甚至还有一个小清单，这很实用，
And I think it's pretty neat that this even has a little checklist
我可以用它来规划万圣节活动。为了让你了解深度研究
that I could use to plan out my Halloween event to give you a sense of how a deep
工具是如何工作的，以下是它在制定研究计划后的大致做法。
researcher works, this is loosely what it does after formulating a research plan.
AI 模型实际上可以同时发起多次联网搜索，
An AI model can actually issue many web searches at the same time
并同时获取多个网页。
and get back multiple web pages at the same time.
这也是使用 AI 研究工具的一个好处。
And this is one of the nice things about using an AI researcher.
它不必一次只做一个网页搜索。
It doesn't have to do the web searches one at a time.
它可以同时进行多个搜索，
It can do many of them at the same time,
这使它在抓取大量网页时非常高效。
which lets it be very efficient in fetching lots of web pages.
系统还可以查看所有这些来源，并快速评估
The system can also take a look at all of these sources and quickly assess
哪些相关，哪些不太相关。
which ones are relevant and which ones are less relevant.
基于此，它可能会决定是否返回进行额外的网页搜索，
And based on that, it may decide whether or not to go back to do additional web
也许使用不同的搜索关键词。
searches, maybe using different web search terms.
最后，在反复进行几轮联网搜索、
Finally, after going around this loop a few times of doing web search,
评估来源，并决定是否返回获取更多来源之后，
evaluating sources, deciding whether or not to go back to get more sources,
它有望判断已经完成。
it'll hopefully decide it's done.
最后，它会获取所有已下载的页面，并可能进行总结
And then lastly, take all of the pages it has downloaded and maybe summarize
并将所有内容综合成一份报告，并附上引用。
and synthesize all that into a report that it adds citations to.
然后它会同时为你提供支持联网搜索的 AI 以及深度研究。
And that it then presents to you both web search-enabled AI as well as deep research.
使用互联网或进行联网搜索。
Use the internet or do web search.
基础版联网搜索 AI 擅长处理这类查询。
The basic web search-enabled AI is good at queries like this.
帮我找一家评价高的健身房。这周迪拜天气怎么样？
Find me a highly rated gym. What's the weather in Dubai this week?
而深度研究，我更倾向于用它来处理
Whereas deep research I would tend to use for tasks
需要综合多方观点的任务。
that require synthesizing multiple views,
比如，如果我想知道每天步行步数对长期健康有什么影响
such as if I want to know what's the impact of daily steps on long-term health
如果我想搜索最新且有科学依据的文章
and if I wanted to search the most recent scientifically justified articles
并认真思考答案。
and think through the answer.
而不是只告诉我网上人们通常怎么说，或者
Rather than just tell me whatever people tend to say on the internet or
如果我想深入思考天气如何影响迪拜的旅游业。
if I wanted to deeply think through how weather affects tourism in Dubai.
同样，不是只取社交媒体网站上的一两个热门答案，
And again, not just take one or two popular answers found on a social media site,
而是去研究天气、研究旅游业，
but to read up on weather, read up on tourism,
研究迪拜，并真正思考其中的影响，从而给我一个更
read up on Dubai and to really think through the implications to give me a more
深思熟虑的答案。这时候深度研究就特别有用。
thoughtful answer. That's when deep research could be particularly helpful.
为了给你另一个思考框架
To give you another framework to think through
什么时候该用联网搜索，什么时候该用深度研究。
when to use web search versus deep research.
如果你有一个想得到答案的单一问题，
If you have a single question that you want answered,
而完成它只需要我花几秒钟、参考少量信息来源，
doing work that would take me just a few seconds based on a handful of sources,
那就是联网搜索非常有用的时候。
that's when web search would be really helpful.
正如我们所见，联网搜索可以自动触发，也可以由用户手动触发，
And web search, as we've seen, can be triggered either automatically or by the user,
而深度研究通常试图得出一组复杂的结论，
whereas deep research often is trying to draw a complex set of conclusions
这可能需要回答多个问题，或涉及多个
that may require answering multiple questions or answering multiple
与某个问题相关的维度。
dimensions that relate to a question.
我认为这就像需要我花几分钟甚至几小时的工作，
And I think of this as doing work that would take me minutes to maybe even hours
如果我是手动完成的话。
if I was doing this manually.
而且我可能希望综合许多信息来源。
And I may want many sources of information, synthesized.
正如我们所见，深度研究通常由用户明确触发。
And as we've seen, deep research is usually triggered explicitly by the user.
除非你在用户界面中选择它，
Unless you select it in the user interface,
大多数 AI 模型不会主动执行深度研究
most AI models would not carry out deep research
并让你等好几分钟才给出答案。
and keep you waiting for many minutes for an answer.
总结一下：如果你问的是“啊，我把手机掉汤里了”，
To recap, if you're asking, oh, I dropped my phone in soup,
它不需要查找任何在线来源。
it doesn't need to look up any online sources.
我们不用担心时效性。它几秒钟内就会给你答案。
We're not worried about freshness. It'll give you an answer in just a few seconds.
这适合查找基本事实、定义
And this is good for finding basic facts, definitions,
以及互联网上常见内容的摘要。
summaries for things that occur commonly on the internet.
联网搜索可能会下载少量信息来源
Web search may download a handful of sources
并且会找到相对最新的信息
and it will find relatively up-to-date information
而且可能需要几十秒才能返回答案。
and it may take many seconds to get you back an answer.
我们已经看到它适合哪些类型的信息。
And we've seen what types of information this is useful for.
最后，深度研究可能会下载几十个甚至更多来源。
And lastly, deep research may download dozens or more sources.
它会获取最新信息，
It will get up-to-date information,
并且会花几分钟甚至更长时间给你返回答案。
and it will spend many minutes or longer to give you back an answer.
它非常擅长回答复杂问题，
And it's great at answering complex questions
需要综合许多知识来源的问题。
that involve synthesizing many sources of knowledge.
查找信息是人们使用 AI 模型最常见的任务之一。
Finding information is one of the most common tasks that people use AI models for.
你已经看到三种不同的路径
You've seen three different paths
可以用来完成这类信息查找任务。
that you can take advantage of for this type of information finding task.
你可以只使用预训练知识、联网搜索或深度研究。
You can use just the pre-trained knowledge or web search or deep research.
我们也梳理了如何以及何时使用这些不同的选项。
And we also walk through how and when to use these different options.
我想确保你对以下问题有很好的直觉：
I want to make sure that you have good intuitions about
什么时候使用每个选项。
when to use each of these options.
那么接下来我们来看看本模块的一个实践动手实验。
So let's go on to take a look next at a practice hands-on lab for this module,
我觉得你会觉得这是一个有趣的方式来比较
which I think you'll find a fun way to compare
和对比这三种选项各自的作用。
and contrast what each of these three options do.
更重要的是，它也会帮助你磨练何时使用每种选项的直觉。
And more importantly, it will also help you hone your intuition on when to use each.
在这个模块中，你学习了如何使用 AI 模型来查找信息。
In this module, you learn how to use AI models to find information.
在这个实践实验中，你可以探索联网搜索、
In this practice lab, you can explore how web search,
深度研究以及不同的提示词如何影响 AI 模型的输出。
deep research and different prompts affect the AI model's output.
我们来看看。
Let's take a look.
打开实验时，它会先提供一个关于如何使用该实验的教程。
When you open up the lab, it starts off with a tutorial on how to use the lab.
我先在这里把它关掉。
And I'm just going to close it out here.
你随时可以通过上面这个按钮再次访问这个教程。
You can always access this tutorial again via this button up here.
我希望你做的是按照这里写明的说明操作，完成后，
And what I hope you do is follow the instructions written here and when you're done,
点击 Mark as complete 将这一项标记为已完成。
click Mark as complete to mark this item as completed.
首先，下面这些按钮对应着你可以尝试的不同内容。
First, these buttons down here correspond to different things you might try.
比如这个 Current Events（时事）按钮，会比较同一个问题在是否启用联网搜索时的不同结果。
So this one, Current Events, compares a question with and without web search.
那么“67 meme”是什么？左边这个是没有使用联网搜索的结果。
So what's the 67 meme? This on the left is without web search.
右边这个则是启用了联网搜索的结果。
The one on the right is with web search enabled.
如果你把它们对比一下：没有联网搜索时，它会给出这些回答。
And if you compare them, without web search, it gives these answers.
它不知道这个 meme。
It doesn't know about the meme.
但启用联网搜索后，它还会告诉你什么是 67 meme，
But with web search, it tells you what this 67 meme is as well
以及这个 meme 的起源。
as the origins of this meme.
如果你想的话，还可以继续追问：
And if you want, you can also follow up and ask,
我该如何在 black tie 礼服派对上恰当使用“67”这个梗？
How do I use 67 appropriately at a black tie tuxedo party?
然后点击这个红色按钮，查看它的回答。
and then hit this red button to go see its answer.
我们点击上面的 New Chat，返回主页。
Let's go back to the home page by clicking New Chat up here.
我希望你也试试其他示例，
And I hope you try out the other examples,
比如“帮我找一家评分很高的健身房”，然后点击 Compare（比较），
such as "Find me a highly rated gym" and hit Compare,
或者“下一部 Avengers 电影定在什么时候上映？”
or when's the next Avengers movie scheduled?
或者“今天美国发生了什么重要新闻？”
Or what major news happened today in the US?
或者自由输入你所在的国家，然后比较这些结果
Or feel free to enter your own country and compare these results with
在启用与不启用联网搜索时的差异。
and without web search.
这里的这个示例展示了联网搜索
This example over here shows the difference between web search,
与 Deep Research（深度研究）之间的区别：前者用这个地球图标表示，后者用这个显微镜图标表示。
denoted by this globe icon, versus Deep Research, denoted by this microscope icon.
那么，灰市肽类产品有多安全？请使用高质量信息来源。
So how safe are grey market peptides? Use high quality sources.
这会让你看到联网搜索结果大概是什么样的。
And this will give you a sense of what web search results look like.
并与 Deep Research（深度研究）的结果对比。
Versus Deep Research results.
我希望你运行一下，看看会得到什么结果。
I hope you run it and see what results you get.
再来看一个示例。
One more example.
如果我想问：我可以把火箭推进的怪兽卡车停在车库里吗？
If I want to ask, can I keep my rocket-propelled monster truck in my garage,
如果你问它这个问题，AI 模型可能知道也可能不知道答案。
if you ask it this question, the AI model may or may not know the answer.
但如果你同时上传租赁协议，
But if you were to also upload the lease agreement,
那么也许你的租赁协议，
Then maybe your lease agreement,
也就是规定你租房条款的文件，可能会对此有限制。
which states the terms under which you are renting your place, may have restrictions on that.
所以你会看到不同的回答，这取决于你是否上传
And so you will see different answers depending on whether or not you upload
额外信息——在这个示例中，
additional information, in this case,
就是一份有助于 AI 给出更周全回答的租赁协议。
a lease agreement that is helpful for the AI to give you a thoughtful answer.
在这个模块里，我们还没有详细讨论上传你自己的文件，
We haven't talked much yet about uploading your own files in this module,
但这是我们在后面的视频中会更深入探讨的内容。
but it's something we'll dive into more deeply later in these videos.
不过你现在就可以试着玩玩看。
But feel free to play with this now.
最后，这里有一个有趣的示例：一个满是拼写错误的“为什么猫会盯着墙看？”版本。
Lastly, one fun example here is a version of "Why do cats stare at walls?" with lots of typos.
这里有一个语法格式规范、没有拼写错误的版本，
Here's one with nicely formatted grammar, no typos,
你会发现两者的回答可能惊人地相似，
and you'll find that the answers are maybe surprisingly similar,
也就是说 AI 系统很擅长回答这类问题，
that the AI system is pretty good at answering a question like this,
即使里面有很多拼写错误。
even if there's lots of typos.
尝试完下面这些按钮对应的示例后，
Once you've tried out these examples reflected by these buttons down here,
你可以自己想一个例子，比如“今天 Palo Alto 的天气适合野餐吗？”
come up with your own, like, "Is the weather good for a picnic in Palo Alto today?"
然后分别尝试使用和不使用联网搜索，看看会得到什么答案。
And try this with or without web search and see what answers you get.
或者选一个你自己的例子，比较使用联网搜索得到的结果
Or pick your own example and try comparing the results you get using web search
以及（如果你愿意）上传自己的文件后的结果。
and if you want, uploading your own files.
以上就是模块 1 的内容了。走到这一步，你做得很好。
So that's it for module 1 of this course. Great job getting this far.
我希望你喜欢在这个实验里探索。
I hope you enjoy playing around with the lab.
接下来，请和我一起进入下一个模块，你将了解如何把 AI
Next, please join me in the next module where you hear about using AI
当作思考伙伴，包括让它与你头脑风暴，
as a thought partner, including having it brainstorm with you
并和你一起探索想法。
and explore ideas with you.
这帮助我确定了很多项目的方向，
This has helped me shape the direction of many projects,
我相信你也会觉得它很有用。
and I'm confident you'll find it useful too.
我们还会探索如何让 AI 帮助你写作和编辑。
And we'll also explore getting AI to help you with your writing and editing.
我们下一个模块见。
I'll see you in the next module.
AI 最有用的用途之一，就是充当思考伙伴。
One of the most helpful uses of AI is as a thought partner.
当我试图想清楚一个复杂问题，或做一个复杂决定时，
When I'm trying to think through a complex problem or make a complex decision,
如果能有一位真人专家作为思考伙伴，会很棒。
it's nice to have a human expert as a thought partner.
也就是一个可以和你把问题讨论清楚的人。
That is someone to talk things through with.
但如果身边没有现成的真人专家，AI
But if there isn't a human expert readily available, AI,
实际上对很多领域都了解不少，
which actually knows a lot about a lot of things,
可以成为这方面非常好的资源。
can be a really good resource for this.
我们会一起看多个这样的例子。
We'll go through together multiple examples of this.
不过作为开始，头脑风暴就是一个很好的应用场景。
But to get started, brainstorming is one great such use case.
我知道很多人会请 AI 帮忙头脑风暴出一堆想法，
Now, I know a lot of people ask AI to help brainstorm lists of ideas,
但其实有更有效的使用方式，
but there are more effective ways to use it
让它作为头脑风暴伙伴，而不只是让它生成一个列表。
as a brainstorming partner than just having it generate a list.
我来给你看看我的意思。
Let me show you what I mean.
根据 OpenAI 发布的 ChatGPT 对话分析数据，
According to data released by OpenAI analyzing ChatGPT conversations,
大约一半的 ChatGPT 对话是在寻求写作和实用指导。
about half of ChatGPT chats are asking for writing and practical guidance.
事实上，创意构思占所有对话的 3.9%，几乎 4%。
And in fact, creative ideation accounts for 3.9%, almost 4%, of all chats.
我发现用 AI 来帮我头脑风暴非常有价值。
I found using AI to help me brainstorm to be really valuable.
我来和你分享一些做法。
Let me share with you some ways to do so.
AI 很擅长生成各种选项。
AI can be pretty good at generating options.
有一个常见的创造力测试，
There's a common creativity test
要求人们说出砖头的 200 种潜在用途。
which asks people to name 200 potential uses for a brick.
那么，给你这样一块砖头，你能想到它有多少种用途？
So given a brick like this, how many uses can you think of for it?
这其实相当难。
This is actually pretty difficult.
有人会想，哦，它可以当镇纸，也许可以当花盆，还有哦，
Some people think, oh, it could be a paperweight, maybe a planter, and oh,
我猜它也能用来盖房子吧。
it could be used to build a house, too, I guess.
但要想到 200 个例子并不那么容易。
But to come up with 200 examples is not that easy.
但如果你问 AI 模型，你很有可能会得到一长串想法，
But if you ask an AI model, there's a good chance you can come up with a long list
而如果你真的想用砖头做点什么，你的角色会是
of ideas and your role if you're actually trying to use a brick for something would
评估这些选项，挑出哪些是
be to evaluate these options to pick out which ones are the ones that
你喜欢的。在头脑风暴中，常见原则是点子越多越好。
you like. In brainstorming, a common guidance is the more ideas the better.
所以，有时候让 AI 生成大量想法供你挑选，可以成为
And so sometimes having AI generate a lot of ideas for you to pick from can be a
找到一两个好点子的有效方法。
powerful way to find one or two good ideas.
这可能是 AI 作为头脑风暴伙伴更常见的用法。
So this is the maybe more common use of AI as a brainstorming partner.
我想给你看一种不同形式的头脑风暴，
I want to show you a different form of brainstorming in
在这种形式中，你给它更多上下文，然后也和 AI 进行更长时间的迭代，
which you give it more context and then also iterate with the AI longer,
也就是进行更长的来回对话，帮助你得到更好的选项。
meaning have a longer back and forth conversation to help get you to better options.
所以如果你告诉它：帮我制定一个健身计划。
So if you tell it, help me build a workout plan.
我 38 岁，初学者水平，有 10 磅的哑铃，每天有 15 分钟。
I'm 38, beginner level, have 10 pound dumbbells and 15 minutes a day.
那么 AI 可能会给出相当普通的回答，比如三个健身计划。
Then the AI may give fairly generic answers, like three workout plans.
从 10 个深蹲、10 个俯卧撑开始。
Start with 10 squats, 10 push-ups.
挺合理、很明智、符合常识的回答。
Pretty reasonable, very sensible, common sense answer.
但如果你想要更有创意的选项，给它更多上下文会有帮助。
But if you want more creative options, giving it more context can be helpful.
所以如果你说：我坚持不了这些，
So if you say, I can't stick to these,
给我一些坚持下去的窍门。我有一张蹦床，
give me hacks to stay on track. I have a trampoline
和一只猫，这会鼓励它给你一些与蹦床和猫相关的锻炼选项，
and a cat, by encouraging it to give you trampoline and cat-related workout options,
这是一种不常见的锻炼方式。
which is an unusual way of approaching workouts.
它可能会让你考虑蹦床间歇，或者由猫触发的微锻炼，
It may ask you to consider trampoline breaks or cat-triggered micro workouts
比如每次你看到你的猫摇尾巴或类似动作时，
where maybe every time you see your cat wag its tail or something,
就去做一小会儿锻炼。
go do a tiny little workout.
但这些肯定是更有创意的点子。
But these are certainly more creative ideas.
AI 模型有一些内在的创造力，
AI models have some inherent creativity
因为它们是在互联网上的大量文本上训练的，
because they've trained on a lot of texts on the internet,
而这些文本来自很多非常不同的想法，包括一些有创意的想法。
which come from a lot of very different ideas, including some creative ones.
而且 AI 的输出有一点随机性，所以如果你问它多次，
And AI's output is a little bit random, so if you ask it multiple times,
帮我制定一个健身计划，它可能会给出略有不同的回答。
help me build a workout plan, it'll probably give you slightly different answers.
但如果你给 AI 的是很基础的问题，那么符合常识的、
But if you give the AI basic questions, then common sense,
相对普通的回答，比如深蹲、俯卧撑等等，就更有可能出现。
relatively generic responses like do squats, push-ups and so on are more likely.
我来画一个示意图，
Let me draw a conceptual diagram
横轴表示回答有多独特，
where on the horizontal axis I'm going to plot how unique a response is,
以及回答有多有创意。
how creative a response is.
左边是像普通力量训练这样的回答，比如二头弯举，
So on the left were responses like normal weightlifting exercises, like bicep curls,
这是很常见的，然后是稍微更独特一些的，比如
which is very common sense, to then maybe slightly more unique things like standing
单腿站立，头顶放一块瑜伽砖，
on one leg with a yoga block on your head,
再到真正有创意的，比如“猫触发的微锻炼”。
to the really creative ones like cat-triggered micro workouts.
在纵轴上，我
And on the vertical axis, I'm
要绘制 AI 给出这些不同回答的概率。
going to plot the probability of AI giving these different responses.
事实证明，它给出常识性回答的可能性，要远高于给出
And it turns out that it's much more likely to give a common sense response than a
高度独特、富有创意的回答。
highly unique, creative response.
这是有原因的。
There's a reason for this.
也就是说，它是在互联网
Namely, it was trained on internet,
文本上训练的，而互联网上谈论哑铃弯举的文本，远多于谈论猫
text, and a lot more internet text talking about dumbbell curls than there are cat
触发的微锻炼的文本。
triggered micro workouts.
对大多数问题来说，这其实没问题，
And for most questions this is actually okay
因为互联网上的平均信息大概还算可靠。
because the average information on the internet is probably decently factual.
所以当你在查找信息，比如
So when you're seeking information such
世界上最高的建筑是什么——它其实是 Burj Khalifa，
as what's the tallest building in the world, it's actually the Burj Khalifa,
互联网上的大多数文本都会说它是 Burj Khalifa。
most internet text will say it is the Burj Khalifa.
也有少量文本会提到其他建筑，
There are smaller amounts of text that will name other buildings,
但互联网上的平均回答，或者说最常见的回答，
but the average response, or the most common response on the internet,
对于像“世界最高建筑是什么？”这类问题来说，通常就是符合事实的那一个。
factual one for questions like, what's the tallest building?
但如果你在头脑风暴，那么给出平均信息或最常见的
But if you're brainstorming, then giving the average information or the most common
回答，最终会变成深蹲、俯卧撑，而且几乎从不会出现蹦床休息，
response ends up with squats, push-ups, and almost never trampoline breaks
更不用说基于猫的锻炼了。
and pretty much never cat-based sessions,
这就是为什么如果你让一个 AI 模型和你一起头脑风暴，
which is why if you ask an AI model to brainstorm with you,
你会得到很多常识性想法，而不是更有创意的想法，而这，
you get a lot of common sense ideas rather than the more creative ideas, which,
取决于你的目标，可能是也可能不是你想要的。
depending on your goal, may or may not be what you want.
那么该怎么做？如果你想获得高质量、
So what do you want to do? If you want to get high-quality,
更有创意的想法？
more creative ideas from AI?
我们已经看到，使用基础提示时，你得到的是来自常识空间的回答。
We've seen with a basic prompt, you get responses from the common sense space.
但如果你给 AI 模型更多上下文，比如给出你的年龄、你的水平，
But if you give the AI model more context, so give your age, your level,
还要告诉它你有迷你蹦床、你的猫，以及
but also tell it you have a mini trampoline, your cat, trouble
难以保持动力的问题。不要深蹲。
staying motivated. No squats.
然后这些上下文会把它推向更相关、更有创意的空间，
Then this context pushes it into the more relevant and creative space
并且更有可能给出定制化的回答，
and is more likely to give a custom answer
而不是生成常识性回答。
rather than to generate common sense answers.
在头脑风暴时，你可能遇到的一个问题是，
Now, one problem that you may face when brainstorming is
如果你想提出有创意的想法，
if you're trying to come up with creative ideas,
你其实可以给 AI 模型提供非常多的上下文。
there's so much context you could potentially give the AI model.
那你应该优先告诉 AI 模型哪些上下文？
What should you prioritize telling the AI model?
事实证明，有一个技巧
It turns out there's a technique
非常有助于指导你决定给 AI 模型提供哪些上下文，
that is very helpful for driving what context you decide to give the AI model,
那就是与 AI 反复迭代。
which is to iterate with the AI.
让我演示一下我的意思。
Let me show you what I mean.
如果我想请 AI 帮我头脑风暴偿还债务的计划，
If I want to ask AI to help me brainstorm plans for paying off my debt,
我有 1.1 万美元的信用卡债务，利率 19%，
I have $11,000 of credit card debt at 19% interest,
每月最低还款 40 美元，还有一笔利率 8% 的学生贷款。
monthly minimum payments of $40, a student loan at 8% interest.
还有一笔 900 美元的家庭借款。这提供了不错的背景信息。
And a family loan of $900. So this gives decent background context.
那么你可以做的一件事是，让 AI 不要只给你一个选项或告诉你该
Then one thing you could do is ask AI not to give you one option or tell you what to
怎么做，而是给你多个选项供你选择。
do, but to give you multiple options to choose from.
我通常会请它给我三到五个选项。
I'll often ask it to give me three to five options.
于是 AI 可能会提出几个不同的方案。
And so the AI may come up with a few different plans.
方案 1 是流动性优先，以保留现金。
Plan 1 is liquidity first, to preserve cash.
方案 2 是还清利率最高的贷款。
Plan 2 is to eliminate the highest interest loan.
方案 3 是优先还钱给家人。
Plan 3 is to prioritize paying your family back first.
这些其实都是合理的想法。
So these are all actually reasonable ideas.
而且我还没有给它足够的上下文来判断
And I've not yet given it enough context to know
它应该更倾向于哪个方案。
which of these plans it should favor.
事实证明，要想弄清楚该给 AI 补充哪些额外
And it turns out that one of the really good ways to figure out what additional
上下文，一个很好的方法是就它给你的选项提供反馈，
context to give to AI is to give it feedback on the options it presented to you,
提供高度相关的反馈，让它能继续给你下一组选项。
highly relevant feedback that allows it to then give you the next set of options.
我不喜欢方案 1，它太被动了。
I don't like option 1. It's too passive.
我确实喜欢它们会还清那笔 19% 利息的贷款。
I do like that they are paying off the 19% interest loan.
哦，我还忘了说，我还有 450 美元现金会到账，而且我也快搬家了。
Oh, and I forgot, I actually have $450 cash coming and I'm also moving house soon.
然后有了这些额外的上下文，它现在就能在方案 1、
And then with this additional context, it now knows among plans one,
方案 2 和方案 3 中，大概了解你喜欢什么、不喜欢什么。
two and three maybe what you like and what you don't like.
你可以让它再创建三个新方案。
And you can ask it to create three new plans.
然后，再通过对这些方案给出反馈，
And then once again, by giving it feedback on these plans,
你也在提供额外的上下文，帮助塑造 AI 模型的思考。
you are giving additional context that will help shape the AI model's thinking.
你可以像这样持续迭代一段时间，
And you can keep on iterating like this for a while
直到它给出一个你确实喜欢的方案。
until it comes up with a plan that you do like
然后也许让它为你最喜欢的一个或两个方案
and then maybe have it flesh out the details of the one plan or two plans
补充更多细节。
that you like the most.
我发现，对 AI 认为的好想法给出反馈，
I found that giving feedback to the AI on what it thinks are good ideas is just a
是一种非常有效的机制，可以高效地弄清楚该给 AI 哪些有用的上下文。
very useful mechanism for very efficiently figuring out what's helpful context to give to the AI.
总结一下：如果你在头脑风暴，
To summarize, if you're brainstorming,
可以考虑提前给 AI 尽可能多的相关上下文，
consider giving AI as much of the relevant context as you can in advance,
然后让它给出几个方案，
and then ask it for a handful of options,
再对不同方案给出反馈，并让它给出更多方案，
then give it feedback on the different options and ask it for more options
并多次迭代。
and iterate multiple times.
获得更多方案，给出反馈；获得更多方案，给出反馈。
Get more options, get feedback. Get more options, get feedback.
这样做几轮，直到你有一个或多个让你满意的想法。
And do that a few times until you have one or more ideas that you're satisfied with.
如果你遵循这套头脑风暴方法，
If you follow this recipe for brainstorming,
我想你会发现你能持续获得更有用、更有创意的想法。
I think you'll find you get consistently more useful and creative ideas.
现在，你已经听我多次提到“上下文”这个词了。
Now, you've heard me use the word context quite a few times.
给 AI 模型提供正确的上下文很重要，这样
It's important to give your AI model the right context so
它才足够了解，去做你想让它做的事。
that it knows enough to do what you want it to.
我们来看看下一个视频，了解上下文是如何工作的，
Let's take a look at the next video and how context works
以及它是如何用来生成回答的。
and how it is used to produce a response.
根据心理学家的研究，大多数人一次只能在他们的
According to psychologists, most humans can keep only about seven things in their
活跃工作记忆中记住大约七件事。
active working memory at a time.
这就是为什么记住一份大约七项的购物清单只是勉强可行，
That's why remembering a grocery list of about seven items is just barely doable
如果你没有在想其他事情的话。
if you aren't thinking about other things.
但记住一份 15 或 20 项的购物清单要困难得多。
But remembering a grocery list of 15 or 20 items is much harder.
有趣的是，AI 可以使用大量上下文。
Interestingly, AI can use a large amount of context.
有些模型的上下文长度可以达到数十万个词。
Some models can have context sizes of hundreds of thousands of words.
我们来看看 AI 模型的上下文是如何工作的，以及你如何利用它。
Let's see how an AI model's context works and how you could take advantage of it.
AI 模型可以在非常大量的上下文上进行阅读和推理。
AI models can read and reason over very large amounts of context.
例如，如果你想选择一套公寓，
For example, if you are trying to choose an apartment,
你可以上传数百页的租赁合同，上传租户评价
you can upload hundreds of pages of lease contracts and upload tenant reviews
和社区统计数据，然后让 AI 阅读所有这些内容，
and neighborhood statistics and ask AI to read all of this
告诉你每个方案的优缺点。你可能会写：
and to tell you the pros and cons of each of the options. And you might write.
一个提示词，比如“每个公寓的优缺点”。
A prompt, like pros and cons of each apartment.
先阅读所有内容，并在回答前认真思考。
Read everything and think really hard before answering.
顺便说一句，告诉 AI 认真思考或努力思考是另一种常见的
By the way, telling AI to think hard or think really hard is another common
提示词模式，我们稍后再回来讨论。
prompting pattern that we'll come back to a little bit later.
上下文指的是所有文本和文件，
Context refers to all the text and files
模型使用这些文本和文件来生成针对你问题的定制化回答。
that the model uses to generate its custom response to your query.
如果你给它一个提示词，比如“学习物理与动物学的优缺点”。
If you give it a prompt like pros and cons of studying physics versus zoology.
那么它会基于这个非常有限的提示词生成输出，
Then it will generate an output based on this very limited prompt,
也就是你给它的非常有限的上下文。
very limited context that you have given it.
而这样的回答可能会相当笼统。
And the response will probably be fairly generic.
但如果你给它更多上下文，
But if you give it more context,
比如给它你的职业评估结果和高中课程表，
maybe give it your career assessment results and give it your high school schedule
这样它就知道你一直在上什么课，
so it knows what classes you've been taking.
然后再问同样的问题。
Then ask the same question.
所有这些额外的上下文将帮助它给出更个性化
All this additional context will help it to give a much more custom
也可能更高质量的回答。
and likely higher quality response.
如果你想思考该给 AI 模型哪些上下文，
If you're trying to think about what context to give to the AI model,
想一想，一个值得信赖的顾问为了深入思考
think about what's all the information
和推理所需的所有信息，
that a trusted advisor would need in order to think at length and reason,
然后给你一个很好的回答。
and then give you a good answer to your question.
而一个对你一无所知的智能顾问，如果只是被问到
And a smart advisor that knows nothing about you but is just asked,
学习物理和动物学各自的利弊是什么？
what are the pros and cons of studying physics versus zoology?
它最多也只能给出一个相当笼统的回复
The best it could really do is give a pretty generic response
而不是为你量身定制的，因为上方例子中的上下文里
that's not custom to you because the context in the example on top just doesn't have
没有任何专属于你的信息。
anything specific to you.
AI 模型一开始就带有一定量的内置上下文
An AI model starts with some amount of built-in context
而如今领先的 AI 模型最多可以接受大约十五万
and leading AI models today can accept maybe up to around a hundred
词作为上下文。
and fifty thousand words as context.
这大约相当于 Harry Potter 系列前四五本书的内容量。
And this corresponds to about the first four or five Harry Potter books.
所以这是非常多的文本。
So that's a lot of text.
或者相当于连续几天的语音。
Or to several days of continuous speech.
所以很多人都低估了你可以给 AI 模型提供多少信息、多少上下文。
So many people underestimate how much information or how much context you can give to an AI model.
现在，当你向 AI 模型提问时，默认情况下，
Now, when you ask the AI model a question, by default,
它的上下文会填充若干内容。
its context is filled with a few things.
首先是所谓的系统提示词，
first, there's something called a system prompt,
它通常让 AI 模型知道当前日期是什么，
which usually is how the AI model knows what's the current date,
知道模型名称、基本能力，
knows the name of the model, basic capabilities,
也许还包括一些帮助用户的一般性指令。
maybe general instructions to be helpful to the user.
然后，如果你的 AI 模型能使用联网搜索引擎这类工具，
And then if your AI model is able to use tools like a web search engine,
在这个上下文里也会写入这些工具是什么
in this context will also be written descriptions of what these tools are
以及如何使用它们的描述，比如什么是联网搜索引擎
and how to use them, such as what is a web search engine
以及在你写出提示词之前，它应该如何先使用联网搜索引擎。
and how should it use a web search engine before you've written your prompt.
上下文包括系统提示词和这两项定义。
The context includes the system prompt and these two definitions.
当你随后写下提示词时，你的提示词会被加入 AI 模型的上下文，
And when you then write your prompt, your prompt is added to the AI model's context,
然后它会利用所有这些内容作为输入来生成回复。
and it will then use all of these things as input to generate a response.
例如，你有这些选项：全身、上半身、下半身、拆分、低冲击、力量，
Like you have the options, full body, upper, lower, split, low impact, strength,
输入的文本，也就是你写下的提示词，
the input text, that is the prompts you've written,
以及 AI 的回复，统称为聊天记录。
as well as the AI responses are called the chat history.
聊天记录也会逐步添加到 AI 模型的上下文中。
And the chat history gets incrementally added to the context of the AI model as well.
现在，如果你一开始给 AI 模型更多上下文，
Now, if you start off giving the AI model more context,
比如写更长的提示词，以及
such as write a longer prompt, as well
也许上传几份文档，告诉它更多关于你的锻炼计划
as maybe upload a handful of documents to tell it more about your workout schedule
或锻炼偏好的信息。
or your workout preferences.
那么所有这些文件都可以被纳入 AI 模型的上下文
Then all of these files can be included in the AI model context
并用于生成回复。
and used to generate the response.
现在，如果你继续对话说：我喜欢第一个计划的这一点，
Now, if you continue the conversation to say, I like this about the first plan,
我不喜欢第三个计划的那一点。
I don't like that about the third plan.
你在这里说的话会被加入 AI 模型的上下文
What you say here is added to the AI model context
然后，在这类头脑风暴流程中，这个额外回复会进一步
and then this additional response in this type of brainstorming workflow is further
被添加到上下文中。
added to the context.
这就是为什么每当你让 AI 来回
And this is why whenever you ask the AI to go back
生成更多答案时，
and forth to generate additional answers,
它都知道对话历史中到目前为止说过的所有内容。
it knows everything that's been said so far in the conversational history.
现在，让我把这个话题转到另一个方向。
Now, let me take this in a different direction.
想象你已经像上面这样请它制定锻炼计划，
Imagine you had asked it for the workout plan like I've shown here,
它给了你几个锻炼计划。
and it's given you a few workout plans.
如果你反过来对这些计划给出反馈，
If you were to instead give feedback on these plans,
然后完全转向另一个方向，说：
go in a totally different direction and say,
现在为我妈妈制定一个锻炼计划。
now come up with a workout plan for my mom.
那么，AI 模型已有的大量上下文，包括你的日程安排、
Well, a lot of the context the AI model has, including your schedule,
你的锻炼偏好，这些其实都与你妈妈的锻炼计划
your workout preferences, all that isn't really relevant for your mother's workout
不太相关，我想，除非你们俩一起锻炼。
plan, I guess, unless the two of you work out together.
因此，所有这些上下文都会干扰 AI 系统
And so all this context would be distracting for the AI system
并可能导致它生成更差的回答。
and might lead it to generate a worse answer.
而事实上，很难知道这个回答是否受到了
And in fact, it can be hard to know whether this answer was influenced by the
之前上下文的影响。
previous context.
这就是为什么如果你要转向不相关的话题，
This is why if you're going to go off onto an unrelated topic,
最好开启一个新对话，以便清空上下文
it's better to start a new conversation so that you can empty out the context
并只从新的提示词或只从有帮助的信息开始，
and start with just the new prompt or just the information that's helpful,
针对你想回答的新问题，提供上下文。你已经看到如何利用上下文来——
Context for the new question you want to answer. You've seen how context is used to.
产出高质量的回答，
Produce high quality responses,
思考 AI 模型上下文里有什么，并对其进行管理，
Thinking about what's in the AI model's context and managing that
让它只包含相关信息，
so it has just the relevant information
并且希望不要有太多无关信息，
and hopefully not too much irrelevant information,
虽然它可以忽略少量无关信息，
although it can ignore a little bit of it
这样能帮你在 AI 那里得到更好的回答。
that will help you get better answers from your AI.
处理大量上下文的一种方法是允许 AI 模型访问你的电脑，
One way of handling lots of context is to allow the AI model access to your computer
这样它就能查找相关文件，
so that it can explore relevant files
并只在需要时将相关文件纳入 AI 模型的上下文。
and pull relevant files into the AI model's context only as needed.
下个视频中，我们来看看这个非常强大的技巧。
Let's take a look in the next video at this very powerful technique.
AI 正在超越单纯的聊天界面。
AI is moving beyond just chat interfaces.
你可能听说过像 Claude Cowork 或 Microsoft Copilot Cowork 这样的应用，
You may have heard of applications like Claude Cowork or Microsoft Copilot Cowork,
或者 Google Antigravity。
or Google Antigravity.
这些应用可以在你允许的情况下，
These are applications that can, with your permission,
以智能体方式从你的电脑收集上下文，也就是说，它们可以查找和读取文件。
gather context agentically from your computer, meaning they can find and read files.
从你的电脑里获取完成任务所需的信息。
from your computer in order to give themselves the information they need to do a task.
这是用 AI 完成实际工作的一种令人兴奋的新方式。
This is a new and exciting way of using AI to accomplish real work.
让我举例说明这些 AI 桌面应用的一个常见用例。
Let me illustrate a common use case for these AI desktop apps.
如果你一直在研究某个主题，
If you have been doing research on a topic
而且有一个杂乱的文件夹，里面有很多 PDF 研究报告、图片等等。
and have a messy folder with lots of PDF research reports, images and so on.
你可以使用其中一个应用，
You can, with one of these apps,
让它读取文件夹里的文件，
ask it to read through the files in the folder
并根据它发现的内容提出新的整理方案。
and propose a new organization for it based on what it finds.
在这个例子中，AI 能查看这个文件夹，
In this example, the AI is able to look through this folder
并进行一系列更改：重命名文件、移动文件，
and apply a bunch of changes, renaming files, moving files around,
创建子目录，从而形成更合理的整理结构。
creating subdirectories to come up with a much more sensible organization for this.
我来展示一下实际操作流程。
Let me show you the process of how it's actually done.
你可能一开始会让它先整理文件夹，了解里面有哪些内容，
You might start off asking it to organize a folder first, understand what's there,
然后它可以自动地或以智能体方式查看不同文件的命名方式，
and it can then automatically or agentically look at how different files are named
等它基本弄清楚文件夹里有哪些文件之后。
after it has figured out enough of what the files in this folder are.
然后它会提出一个初步的重新整理方案。
It then comes up with an initial proposal for how to reorganize it.
如果你查看这个初步方案，
And if you take a look at the initial proposal,
你可能会不完全满意，于是再给它一些进一步指示，告诉
you may not be fully satisfied and give it a little bit further instructions to tell
它如何处理这些数据。
it what to do with this data.
最后，它会给出一个改进后的方案。
And finally, it comes up with a refined proposal.
我对此很满意。所以我会说，继续执行这些指令吧。
Which I'm happy with. So I'm going to say go ahead and carry out these instructions.
然后它重新整理我的文件夹，让所有文件更整洁。
And then it reorganizes my folder to make all the files much neater.
AI 桌面应用的工作原理如下。
Here's how AI desktop apps work.
它们由 AI 模型驱动。
They are powered by an AI model.
因此它带有 AI 的预训练知识，
So it comes with the AI's pre-trained knowledge
并且还有一组工具，比如联网搜索，
and it also has a set of tools like web search,
因此，如果完成任务需要，它可以选择执行联网搜索，
so it can choose to carry out a web search if it needs to do so
以完成这项任务，并且还有额外工具可以处理你电脑上的文件。
to accomplish this task and has additional tools to work with files on your computer.
包括搜索文件、读取文件、写入文件，
including the ability to search through files, to read files, to write files,
移动和重命名文件等能力。
to move and rename files, and so on.
因此，当你让桌面应用在你的电脑上执行操作时，
So when asking a desktop app to do things in your computer,
最佳实践流程是告诉它你想完成什么任务，
a best practice workflow would be for you to tell it what task you want done,
例如整理文件夹里的文件。
such as organize the files in the folder.
让 AI 系统提出行动计划，但先不要采取行动。
Let the AI system propose an action plan, but not yet take action.
然后你可以审阅计划，给出批判性反馈，
You can then review the plan, give critique,
如果需要，可以让它更新这个计划。
maybe have it update this plan if needed.
只有当你对方案满意后，才告诉它执行计划，
And only when you're satisfied with it, then tell it to execute the plan,
然后它可以在你的电脑上继续执行。
which it can go ahead and do on your computer.
这些桌面应用的一个巧妙之处在于，
One neat aspect of these desktop apps is
它们能自动探索文件，
that they can automatically explore files
并通过仅在需要时读取文件来管理上下文。
and manage context by reading files only when needed.
如果你用的是 AI 聊天，就需要提前决定上传哪些文件，
If you're using an AI chat, then you have to decide in advance what files to upload
以便为 AI 模型提供上下文。
to give the AI model context.
例如，如果你需要写一份拍摄日程安排，
So for example, if you need to write a schedule for filming,
你可能会上传一份概述拍摄流程的文件。
you might upload a file that outlines your filming procedures.
基于这份文件，它就能生成日程安排。请注意，
And based on that, it can generate a schedule and note
你之前必须提前决定要向 AI 提供哪些上下文。
that you had to decide in advance what context to provide to the AI.
但如果使用 AI 桌面应用，比如你在
But with an AI desktop app, if you start the application in, say,
你的“文档/拍摄”文件夹中启动应用，然后告诉它
your documents/filming folder, then if you tell it,
“为本周拍摄写一份日程安排”，
write a schedule for filming this week,
那么 AI 可以决定浏览这个文件夹中的文件，
then the AI can decide to explore the files in this folder so
从而了解里面有哪些文件。
that it can see what files are there.
加载相关文件，然后在此基础上
Load the relevant files and then on that basis,
判断怎样安排拍摄日程更合适。
figure out what is a good filming schedule.
在这个例子中，令人惊喜的是，
And in this example, surprise, surprise,
它实际上注意到你一位剧组成员的生日就在拍摄那一周。
it actually notices that one of your crew members' birthdays is the week of filming.
因此，也许你会为剧组成员 Mia 安排一场庆祝活动。
And so maybe you'll fold in a celebration for your crewmate Mia.
关于安全使用这些桌面应用，有一点需要注意。
One note on using these desktop apps safely.
桌面应用可以访问、编辑甚至删除你的文件。
Desktop apps can get access to and can edit or even delete your files.
虽然像文件被误删这样的情况很少见，但确实有人遇到过。
And while mishaps like deleted files are pretty rare, they have happened to people.
所以我建议你选择最相关的文件夹来运行 AI 桌面应用，
So I encourage you to choose the most relevant folder to run the AI desktop app in,
例如，与其在你的主文件夹中运行
for example, instead of running this in your home folder
并让它访问你的所有文件，
and giving this access to all your files,
不如只让它访问某个任务真正需要的文件子集，
maybe just give it access to the subset of files it really needs for a task in a
放在某个文件夹中。当 AI 系统发出
certain folder. When the AI system makes
权限请求时。
a permission request.
我建议你仔细查看权限请求，确保你
I would encourage you to carefully review the permission request to make sure you
知道它正在读取和写入什么。
know what it is reading and writing.
因此，我只会让 AI 访问我希望它了解的文档，
And so I'll give AI access only to the documents I wanted to know about
并且只允许它写入我希望它写入的文件或位置。
and let it write only to the files or places I wanted to.
当 AI 桌面应用删除文件时，文件通常不会进入你的回收站。
And when an AI desktop app deletes a file, it often does not go to your Recycle Bin.
所以可能没有办法恢复该文件。
So there may not be a way to recover the file.
如果它编辑文件，其行为与你
And if it edits a file, it behaves a bit differently than
亲自编辑文档时略有不同。
if you were editing the document.
特别是，被编辑过的文件通常没有编辑历史。
And in particular, edited files usually don't have an edit history.
因此，如果它做了你不喜欢的修改，也无法回退。
And so it's not possible to go back if it made some change that you may not like.
所以，在你非常熟悉这些工具之前，
So until you are very familiar with these tools,
我建议你仔细查看它发出的权限请求，以决定
I'd encourage you to look carefully at the permissions requests it makes to decide
哪些操作你允许 AI 系统执行，哪些不允许。
what you do and do not want the AI system to be allowed to do.
AI 桌面协作应用是一个强大的工具，你可以用它让 AI 模型
AI desktop co-working apps are a powerful tool you can use to give an AI model the
具备发现相关上下文，以及执行读取、
ability to discover relevant context as well as to take actions such as reading,
写入、移动、重命名文件等操作的能力。
writing, moving, renaming files.
在最近几节课中，我们经常谈到上下文，而
Now, we've talked about context a lot in these last several videos, and using
尽可能多地使用相关上下文，可以让 AI 系统帮助你完成
as much relevant context as possible enables your AI system to help you with what's
所谓的推理任务，也就是
called reasoning tasks, by which I mean tasks
你希望 AI 思考，也许需要较长时间，以给出尽可能好的
where you want your AI to think maybe for a long time to give you the best possible
答案。让我们继续
answer. Let's go on to
下一节视频，看看用 AI 进行推理的例子。
the next video to see examples of reasoning with AI.
最新的 AI 模型具有很强的推理能力。
The latest AI models have very strong reasoning capabilities.
这意味着，在给定合适上下文时，
What that means is they can think rigorously and at length about the task
它们可以严谨且深入地思考任务。
when given the right context.
我发现自己越来越多地把 AI 当作推理引擎来使用。
I find myself more and more using AI as a reasoning engine.
我们来看一个例子。
Let's take a look.
这是一个“长时间思考有助于获得更好回答”的例子。
Here's an example where thinking for a long time can help get a better response.
如果你正在购车，并在多辆车之间权衡取舍，
If you are car shopping and are considering tradeoffs among multiple cars,
你可能会上传车辆规格表、保险方案、车贷报价，
you might upload spec sheets for the cars, insurance plans, car loan quotes,
以及大量文档。
lots of documents.
然后问：“每辆车各有哪些取舍？”
And then ask, what are the tradeoffs for each car?
“阅读所有内容并认真思考后再回答。”
Read everything and think hard before answering.
AI 模型随后可能会花相当长时间阅读文档，
The AI model may then think for quite a long time to read the documentation,
也许会进行一些在线搜索，然后思考我们为你列出的评估标准
maybe do some online search, then maybe think through what the evaluation criteria
是什么，然后生成报告，列出
are that we write for you and then generate reports on the pros
不同汽车的优缺点。
and cons of different cars.
正如研究购买哪辆车可能涉及收集大量
And just as doing research on what car to buy could involve gathering a lot of
信息，并花一些时间思考利弊。
information and thinking at some length about the pros and cons.
AI 可以帮助证明，随着 AI 模型变得更好，
AI can help prove that as AI models get better,
它们执行长时间任务的能力正在快速增长。
their ability to carry out long-running tasks has grown rapidly.
这是由 METR 组织进行的一项研究，
This is a study by an organization METR,
其中针对不同难度的任务绘制了图表，
which plots for tasks of different levels of difficulty
衡量标准是人类完成该任务需要多长时间。
as measured by how long it'll take a human to do the task.
这是纵轴。
That's the vertical axis.
AI 完成这些任务的能力如何？
How well can AI do these tasks?
例如，在网络上查找一个事实可能只需要人类几秒钟。
So for example, a task like finding a fact on the web may take a human just several seconds.
总结几页文本可能需要人类一个小时。
Summarizing a few pages of text may take a human an hour.
写一篇博客文章，需要几个小时。
Write a blog post, couple hours.
审计法律文件、排查一个复杂的网络安全漏洞，
Audit legal documents, explore a complex cybersecurity vulnerability,
可能需要人类很多小时，等等。
may take a human many hours, and so on.
在 2024、2025 年左右，模型开始能够处理
And around 2024, 2025, models could start to do tasks
从几秒到很多秒，再到几分钟或几十分钟的任务。
that took seconds to many seconds to many minutes or tens of minutes.
到 2025 年，模型完成这些任务的成功率开始变得不错，
And in 2025, models could start to have a decent success rate for doing tasks
这些任务需要人类花越来越长的时间，
that took humans longer and longer and longer,
以至于现在 AI 模型可以完成需要人类花很多、
to the point where now AI models can do tasks that can take humans many,
很多小时才能完成的任务。通常 AI 模型不需要 10 小时来
many hours to do. Often the AI model doesn't need 10 hours to.
完成一个人类需要 10 小时才能完成的任务，
Do a task that takes a human 10 hours to do,
但它花费的时间也会比短短几秒要长一些。
but also takes a bit longer than just a few seconds.
这正是推理模型带来的能力，让 AI 可以非常长时间地思考，以
And this is what reasoning models have enabled for the AI to think at great length in
便完成这些更复杂的任务。
order to do these more complex tasks.
如果你还记得草莓里有多少个 r 的例子，
If you remember the how many r's in strawberry example,
那是一个人类只需几秒钟就能完成的任务。
that's a task that takes a human just a few seconds to do.
几年前，AI 模型有时会弄错这个问题。
And several years ago, AI models used to sometimes get this wrong.
也正是在那个时期，大约 2023、2024 年，你可能听过这样的建议，
And it was also in that era, maybe 2023, 2024, that you may have heard advice,
比如告诉 AI 模型要一步步思考。
like tell the AI model to think step by step.
当时这是个好建议，但现在这个建议基本已经过时了，
And back then, this was good advice, but this advice is largely obsolete now,
我自己也不再告诉我的 AI 模型一步步思考了。
and I no longer tell my AI model to think step by step.
相反，我更可能只是告诉它认真思考，
Instead, I'm more likely to just tell it to think hard,
而它明白这意味着它应该进行长时间推理，
and it knows what that means and that it should reason at length,
不一定是逐步进行，而是以更复杂的方式来完成
not necessarily step by step, but in even more complex ways in order to accomplish the
任务。
task successfully.
所以，与其把 AI 看作只是数草莓里的 r
And so rather than think about AI as counting r's
或者让你告诉它一步步思考，
and strawberries or having you be told to think step by step,
如今你可以向 AI 模型提出更复杂的问题，比如各款车有哪些取舍
today you can ask AI models much more complex questions like what are the trade-offs
或者查看所有这些背景信息
for each car or look at all this context
并帮助创建定制播客的脚本。因此对于这些更复杂的任务，我推荐
and help create a script for a custom podcast. So for these more complex tasks, I recommend.
尝试使用其中一个较新的模型，如果你能访问到一个的话，
Trying to use one of the more modern models if you're able to access one,
而且很可能已经有比幻灯片上列出的模型更新的模型
and there may well be models even more modern than the ones listed on the slide
现在可供你使用。
that could be available to you now.
这就是 AI 推理，或者说 AI 长时间思考的运作方式。
So this is how AI reasoning or how AI thinking at length works.
如果你让它规划一天内游览罗马五个地标的最快路线，
If you ask it to plan the fastest way to visit five landmarks in Rome in one day,
那么它可能想要收集相当多的信息来核实。
then it might want to gather quite a lot of information to check.
通过联网搜索查看地图距离、估算步行时间、查询开放时间，
Map distances via web search, estimate walking times, search opening hours,
重新排序各个停留点等等，然后生成优化后的行程。
reorder the stops and so on, and then generate your optimized itinerary.
推理过程可能需要 AI 长时间思考，
The reasoning process may require the AI to think at length
并反复收集额外信息，
and repeatedly gather additional information,
然后再继续思考，直到它对答案感到满意。
and then to think some more until it's satisfied with the answer.
从概念上讲，你可以把推理想象成这样一个过程。
Conceptually, you can think of reasoning as a process like this.
给定你的提示词和其他输入上下文，
Given your prompt and other input context,
它会利用这些上下文推理或思考一段时间。
it will reason or think for a while using that context.
然后根据它进行到哪一步，
And then depending on where it gets to,
它可能会决定已经完成，然后直接给出最终答案。
maybe it'll decide it's done and then just give you the final answer.
或者，在思考一段时间后，
Alternatively, after thinking for a while,
它可能会决定需要使用工具来收集更多信息，
it may decide that it needs to use a tool to gather more information,
可能是通过联网搜索，或者从你的电脑中读取更多文件
maybe via web search or maybe by reading more files from your computer
如果它是桌面应用的话。
if it's a desktop app.
然后利用这些额外的上下文继续推理更长时间
And then use that additional context to reason longer
直到它再次决定要么使用工具收集更多信息，要么决定任务已经完成。
until it either again decides to use a tool to gather more information or decides it's done.
因此，它可以进行几轮信息收集
And so it can go through a few rounds of gathering more information
并推理更长时间，才决定答案足够好、可以呈现给你。
and reasoning longer before it decides the answer is good enough to present to you.
如果你正在处理复杂任务，并希望模型深入思考，
If you are working on a complex task and you want the model to think at length,
那么一个方法是直接告诉模型去思考。
then one way to do so is to just tell the model to think.
一些热门 AI 模型提供商的界面中会提供“思考”选项。
A few of the interfaces among the popular AI model providers will have a thinking option.
如果你选择这个选项，就是在提示模型
And if you select that option, that's a cue to the model
你希望它思考更长时间。
that you want it to think longer.
或者，你也可以在提示词中直接告诉它认真思考
Alternatively, in your prompt, you can also just tell it to think really hard about
这件事，它通常会遵循你的指示。
this, and it'll usually obey your instructions.
或者，有些人会使用 ultra think 这个短语。
Or some people will use the phrase ultra think.
这也是模型能理解的另一个关键词，用来提示它，你知道，
And that's another keyword that the models understand as a cue to, you know,
认真思考这件事。
think really hard about it.
如果你这样做，AI 模型有时会思考几十秒，甚至
And if you do so, an AI model will sometimes think for many tens of seconds or even
几分钟，有时甚至超过 10 分钟，以便给你一个好答案。
minutes or maybe sometimes even over 10 minutes in order to give you a good answer.
尤其是在使用推理或思考类模型时。
Especially with reasoning or thinking models.
我也鼓励你试着给模型一些困难任务，看看它能为你做什么。
I also encourage you to try giving the model hard tasks to see what it can do for you.
比如，如果你正在创办一家初创公司，
So if you are building a startup,
也许给它大量关于你正在做什么的背景信息
maybe give it lots of context on what you're doing
也许让它为一家现金有限的四人创业公司设计一份总体计划。
and maybe tell it to design a top line plan for a four-person startup with limited cash.
我鼓励你把真实的工作任务交给 AI 模型，
I encourage you to give the AI model real job tasks,
也就是你真正想仔细思考或解决的问题。
real problems that you want to think through or that you want to solve.
而为了让它更有可能成功，
And as part of setting up for success,
尽量给它一个人类专家为完成该任务所需的全部背景信息
try to give it all the context that a human expert would need in order to complete
这项任务，以确保 AI 模型拥有足够的信息
the task to make sure that the AI model has the sufficient information
也就是任何人成功完成该任务真正需要的信息。
that really anyone would need to do the task successfully.
总结一下，如果你希望用 AI 对文本问题进行长时间推理，
To wrap up, if you want to use AI to reason at length about text problems,
我鼓励你使用可用的最佳模型。
I encourage you to use the best models available.
最佳模型通常比可能早 6 到 12 个月的模型更好。
The best models are often better than models that are maybe 6 to 12 months older.
记住，给它完成任务所需的足够上下文。
Remember, to give it as much context as is needed to carry out the task.
可以试着把困难任务交给它，看看它能做什么。
It's okay to try giving a hard task to see what it can do.
所以不要只给它琐碎的任务。
So don't just give it trivial tasks.
最后，要么选择思考模式，要么直接在提示词中告诉它努力思考。
And lastly, either select thinking mode or just tell it in the prompt to think hard.
我们已经讲过什么时候使用前沿模型会更有帮助，
We've spoken about when it's helpful to use the cutting edge models,
但事实证明，即使是最新的模型也存在一些常见问题，
but it turns out even the most up to date models have some common issues,
其中之一就是倾向于告诉你它认为你想听的话。
one being the tendency to tell you whatever it thinks you want to hear.
这被称为“迎合倾向”。
This is called sycophancy.
我们继续看下一个视频，了解如何应对 AI 模型的这种行为。
Let's go on to the next video to see how to manage this behavior of AI models.
AI 模型会采取一些行动来试图取悦你，
AI models will act in ways to try to please you
由于它们的训练方式，
because of the way they've been trained,
它们有很强的偏向，会告诉你你想听的话。
they have a strong bias to tell you what you want to hear.
这被称为“迎合倾向”。
This is called sycophancy.
避免它是一种关键的提示能力，包括以中立方式进行提示
And avoiding it is a key prompting skill and involves prompting neutrally
并保持上下文信息基于事实。
and keeping context factual.
我们来看看如何避免迎合倾向，
Let's take a look at how to avoid sycophancy,
因为这会帮助你从 AI 那里获得更好的回答
because this will help you get much better answers from your AI
当你受到约束时。
if you're constrained.
远程工作与办公室工作的利弊。
The pros and cons of remote work versus in-office work.
你问它：“你不觉得远程工作比办公室工作更好吗？”
And you ask it, don't you think remote work is better than office work?
问题中的这种措辞会暴露你希望得到什么答案。
This word in the question gives away what you're hoping the answer is.
AI 很可能会说：“是的。远程工作有很多优势。”
And AI will probably say yes. Remote work offers many advantages.
相反，如果你问：“办公室工作是否真的效率更高？”
In contrast, if you were to ask, is it true that office work is more productive,
那么它很可能会同意你，说办公室工作有这些显著的好处。
then it will probably agree with you that office work has these strong benefits.
所以，取决于你如何提问，
So depending on how you ask the question,
它往往会强化你自己的偏好和偏见，
it will tend to reinforce your own preferences, your own biases,
而这可能不是最有帮助的，如果你要做出客观、
and this may not be the most helpful thing for you to make objective,
基于事实的决策。
fact-based decisions.
在 Washington Post 对 ChatGPT 回复的一项研究中，
In a study by the Washington Post on ChatGPT responses,
它更可能回复这样的短语，比如“没错。”
it was much more likely to respond with phrases like, that's correct.
“好观点。你方向是对的”，而不是“不太对”。
Good point. You're on the right track compared to not quite right.
事实并非如此。
That's not the case.
实际上，它强烈表示同意的次数大约比不同意多 10 倍。
Or actually, and in fact, it tended to agree strongly about 10 times more than it disagreed.
而一些 ChatGPT 模型甚至会说出“老兄，”
And some models from ChatGPT have said things like, dude,
你眼都不眨就说出了很有深度的话。
you just said something deep without even flinching.
你百分之一千是对的。
You're 1,000% right.
虽然一些用户喜欢 AI 这样附和自己，
And while some users appreciate AI agreeing with them like this,
我个人觉得，让 AI 只是一味同意我说的任何话，并没有那么有用，
I personally don't find it that useful to have AI just tend to agree with whatever I
甚至是在我不正确的时候也是如此。
say even when I'm not right.
虽然领先的 AI 模型公司正在努力减少迎合倾向，
While leading AI model companies are working to reduce sycophancy,
但它仍然是个问题。
it is still a problem.
模型通过人类反馈被训练成有用的助手，
Models are trained to be helpful assistants using human feedback,
而这会强化迎合倾向。
and this reinforces sycophancy.
例如，如果你问一个 AI 模型：我觉得做个内向的人更好，你不觉得吗？
For example, if you ask an AI model, I feel like it's better to be an introvert, don't you?
如果这个 AI 模型回应说：这个想法很有意思，我倾向于同意，原因如下。
If the AI model were to respond, that's an interesting idea. Here's why I tend to agree.
那么大多数人更可能点击反馈按钮上的“赞”，因为，
Then most people are more likely to hit thumbs up on the feedback button because,
你知道，这是个让人感觉不错的回答。
you know, it's a nice answer, makes you feel good.
但如果 AI 说：不一定，两种类型，内向者和外向者，
But if AI were to say, not necessarily, both types, introverts and extroverts,
都各有真实的权衡。
carry real trade-offs.
你知道，人们对那样的回答感觉就没那么好，而且
You know, people just don't feel as good about that answer and
所以他们更不可能点赞，甚至可能点踩。
so they're less likely to hit thumbs up or may even hit thumbs down
由于这类反馈，AI
because of this type of feedback, AI,
随后会被训练去生成更多能获得点赞的回答。
which is then trained to generate more answers that lead to thumbs up.
正向反馈会引导它学会更频繁地、巧妙地同意人们。
Positive feedback will lead it to learn to try subtly to agree with people more often than not.
这就导致了迎合倾向。
And this leads to sycophancy.
迎合倾向看起来像是在帮你，但有时实际上会降低回答质量。
And sycophancy feels helpful, but actually degrades answer quality sometimes.
迎合倾向有时可能更容易被发现。
Maybe sycophancy is easier to spot.
如果你说：我对这篇文章感到非常自豪，你觉得怎么样？
If you were to say, I'm really proud of this essay, what do you think?
它们很可能会同意你。
Well, they'll probably agree with you.
但另一些时候，迎合倾向更难被察觉。
But other times it's harder to detect sycophancy.
如果你说：分析这些数据，
If you were to say, analyze this data
并找出本季度所有表现良好的指标。
and find all the positive measures of performance this quarter.
你就是在悄悄暗示：你在寻找公司表现的正面指标。
You're subtly signaling that you're looking for positive measures of the company's performance.
所以它更可能说出类似“数据清楚显示收入增长、
And so it's more likely to say something like data clearly shows revenue growth,
强劲的留存率、不断改善的利润率”，
strong retention, improving margins
而更不可能指出问题。为了避免循环迎合，
and less likely to point out problems. To avoid circularity,
请尝试用中性的方式提问，不要给出任何暗示，
try to use neutral framing of your questions and avoid giving any hints
暗示你想要的答案是什么。
as to what is the answer you want.
想听到什么。
to hear.
例如，如果我问：碳税难道对小企业有害吗，
So, for example, if I were to ask aren't carbon taxes bad for small businesses,
我其实是在告诉它我希望得到什么答案。
I'm really telling it what answer I'm hoping for.
相比之下，一个更中性的提示是：碳税在多大程度上（如果有的话）
In contrast, a more neutral prompt would be to what extent, if at all,
会影响小企业？
do carbon taxes affect small businesses?
如果有人读到右边这个问题，
If someone reads the question on the right,
其实并不清楚他们想要什么答案。
it's actually not clear what answer they want.
所以 AI 模型更难表现出迎合倾向。或者如果你问：
So it's harder for an AI model to be sycophantic. Or if you were to ask,
你同意 AI 会创造大量工作岗位吗？
do you agree that AI will create a lot of jobs?
我实际上碰巧同意，但如果我是在认真做研究，
I actually happen to agree, but if I'm actually doing research,
我不希望它只告诉我想听的话。
I don't want it to just tell me what I want to hear.
相反，你可以问：当前关于 AI 对就业影响的研究怎么说？
Instead, you can ask, what does current research say about AI's effect on jobs?
或者不要问：远程工作会降低员工生产力吗？
Or instead of asking, does remote work reduce worker productivity?
可以问：远程工作与办公室工作的生产力相比如何？
Maybe ask, how does productivity compare between remote and in-office work?
一个常见做法是列出两个选项，比如远程工作和办公室工作，
One common pattern is to lay out two options, such as remote and in-office work,
然后直接让它比较两者的优缺点，
and just ask it for pros and cons of the comparison,
但不要暗示你希望其中哪一个更占上风。
but without hinting which of the two options I am hoping will come out ahead.
所以你不觉得那是有史以来最好的视频吗？哦。
So don't you think that was the best video ever? Oh.
你觉得你刚看的这些视频有哪些优缺点？
What do you think of the pros and cons of the videos you just saw?
有时候听到你想听的话很舒服，
Sometimes it's nice to be told what you want to hear,
但通常这不会帮助你把工作做得更好。
but generally that won't help you to do better work.
迎合倾向，尽管人们做了很多努力去克服它，
Sycophancy, despite a lot of attempts to combat it,
仍然是当今实际使用 AI 时普遍存在的问题之一。
is still one of the pervasive issues with practical AI usage today.
因此，运用本视频中的这些策略，
And so implementing the strategies from this video,
尤其是采用更中性的表述方式，
especially taking more neutral framing,
会帮助你从 AI 模型那里获得更客观、更有价值的反馈。
will help you get more objective and valuable feedback from AI models.
现在，人们使用 AI 最常见的任务之一是写作。
Now, one of the most common tasks that people use AI for is writing.
我们继续看下一个视频，了解如何借助 AI 模型来帮助你
Let's go on to the next video to see how to work with AI models to help with your
写作。OpenAI 的一项研究显示，写作占人们要求 ChatGPT 完成的
writing. In a study by OpenAI, writing accounted for 24% of tasks
任务的 24%。
that people ask ChatGPT to do.
这是占比最大的一类任务。
This is the single largest group of tasks.
写作实际上是一种思考。我发现我写作时必须思考。
Writing is really a kind of thinking. I find that when I'm writing, I have to think.
而 AI 非常擅长思考和推理，因此可以在这方面帮助你。
And so AI, which is really good at thinking and reasoning, can help you with this.
但只是让 AI 替你写，往往会产生 AI slop（空洞内容），
But just asking AI to write for you often leads to AI slop,
也就是听起来像 AI 写出来的文字，总感觉不同于人类
or writing that sounds like AI writing, which somehow feels different than human,
深思熟虑的写作。
thoughtful writing.
我们来看看一些技巧，让 AI 更有效地为你写作，
Let's take a look at some techniques for getting AI to write effectively for you
以及如何利用 AI 推理并避免 AI slop。
and how to take advantage of AI reasoning and avoid AI slop.
是什么导致了 AI slop？
What makes AI slop?
许多人已经注意到，AI 写出的文字里经常出现长破折号（em dash）。
Many people have noticed that AI writing often includes the em dash.
也就是长破折号，出现频率远高于普通人类写作。
That is the long dash, much more than normal human writing.
在社交媒体网站 Bluesky 上，
On the social media site Bluesky,
自 ChatGPT 发布以来，长破折号的使用量一直在上升。
the use of the em dash has been trending upward ever since the release of ChatGPT.
最近一项调查显示，40% 的美国员工最近一个月里收到过
A recent survey showed that 40% of US-based employees have recently received work
工作中的 AI slop。
slop in the last month.
AI slop 这个术语指的是由 AI 生成、粗看还不错的内容，
And the term AI slop refers to content that's generated by AI and that looks good
但经不起仔细阅读。
if you don't read it too carefully.
或许单独看每个句子都写得不错，
So maybe every sentence read in isolation sounds like it's well written,
但整体上，文章就是缺乏实质内容。
but collectively, the text just lacks substance.
感觉像是没有经过深入或仔细思考写出来的。
It feels like it was written without much deep or careful thought.
AI slop 的一个特点是经常包含这样的句子：
One property of AI slop is that it often contains sentences like this,
“但它确实改变了一切。”
but it does change everything.
这类文字含糊、空洞，却又显得过于重要。
It's kind of vague, empty sounding, but also somehow overly important sounding text.
AI 独特的写作风格来自它倾向于过度使用的
AI's distinctive writing style comes from certain words and patterns
某些词语和句式。
that it tends to overuse.
AI 往往使用更少的不同词汇，并过度使用某些词和短语。
AI tends to use fewer unique words and overrepresents some words and phrases.
例如，AI 往往过度使用 nuanced 和 delve 这两个词，
For example, AI tends to overuse the words nuanced and delve
而且它比大多数人更爱使用三项排比。
and it tends to use lists of three more than most people will.
它还倾向于使用更少的名词，产生这样的短语：
And it tends to use fewer nouns, leading to phrases like,
“这是一篇结构严谨、见解深刻的论文。”
this is a robustly structured and highly insightful paper.
还有这种 “not X but Y” 句式：“不只是关于速度，更是关于可用性。”
And this, not X but Y, is not just about speed, it's about availability.
事实上，我在社交媒体上注意到越来越多这种 “not X
In fact, I've been noticing on social media a lot more of this not X
but Y” 类型的措辞，而且 X 和 Y 往往
but Y type of verbiage, often with X
都是含糊的词，比如“这不是关于基础设施，而是关于架构。”
and Y both vague things like it's not about infrastructure, it's about architecture.
像这样的很多说法都很含糊，
And a lot of phrases like those are just vague
并不能反映出真正深刻的观点。
and don't reflect a deeply insightful point of view.
有趣的是，由于人类大量使用 AI 模型，
Interestingly, because humans are using AI models so much,
人类自己也越来越像 AI 那样说话。
humans are themselves starting to sound more like AI.
而且自 ChatGPT 发布以来，
And humans, ever since ChatGPT was released,
人们在播客和演讲中更多使用 delve 这个词。
are using the word delve more in podcasts and talks.
无论是即兴发言还是备稿演讲都是如此。
And this is true both for spontaneous speech as well as for prepared speeches.
所以这不仅仅是人们用 AI 帮自己写稿的情况。
So this isn't just a case of people using AI to write scripts for them.
看起来，人们是在大量使用 AI 的过程中，
It looks like people are picking up speech patterns or texting patterns from
习得了一些说话或发消息的模式。
spending a lot of time with AI.
那么，有什么更好的写作方式可以避免产生 AI slop 呢？
So what's a better way to write that avoids generating AI slop?
我觉得你会发现一个很有用的技巧：渐进式提纲，
One technique that I think you'll find helpful is to use progressive outlining in
也就是不要一开始就让 AI 写最终文本，
which you don't ask AI to write the final text right away,
而是先让它写一个提纲，
but instead have it write an outline,
在生成最终文本之前，完善提纲并反复迭代几次。
refine the outline and iterate a few times before having it generate the final text.
例如，这里有一个提示词：
For example, here's a prompt that says,
“我在写一篇文章，讲的是使用 AI 的小团队比不使用 AI 的
I'm writing an article about small AI teams moving faster than large teams
大团队行动更快。”
that don't use AI.
“我只是想说明，这不是一个中立的提示词”
And I just want to acknowledge that this is not a neutral prompt
这里我让 AI 帮我判断小型 AI 团队是否真的行动更快。
where I'm asking AI to help me decide if small AI teams do move faster.
但相反，这里是从某个特定角度来写一篇文章，
But instead, this is writing an article from a certain point of view,
但你也可以让 AI 去研究支持和反对这个假设的证据。
but you can ask AI to research evidence for and against this hypothesis.
因此 AI 模型可能会联网搜索并找到若干篇文章。
So the AI model may search online and find a handful of articles.
接下来，如果你希望它帮你头脑风暴出故事的几个方案
Next, if you wanted it to help you brainstorm a handful of options for the story
大纲，你可以让它头脑风暴或创建三个不同的大纲选项。
outline, you can tell it to brainstorm or to create three different outline options.
也许告诉它要包含一个反驳论点部分
Maybe tell it to include a counterargument section
还可以提供或上传一些来自 AI 团队的故事，比如
and also provide or upload a handful of stories from AI teams, say,
你合作过的团队。有了这些输入上下文，
that you work with. With this input context,
AI 可能会返回几个不同的选项，展示文章大纲
the AI may give back a few different options for what the outline for your article
可能是什么样子。
might look like.
方案 1 可以是先讲三个故事，然后以一个论点作结。
Option 1 could be to tell the three stories and then conclude with a thesis.
方案 2 可能会探讨 AI 团队工作的不同模式，等等。
Option 2 might explore different patterns of how AI teams work and so on.
然后按照你在“用 AI 头脑风暴”中学到的方法，
Then following what you saw in how to brainstorm with AI,
你可以对这些选项给出反馈。
you might give feedback on these options.
所以你可能会说：我们用方案 1，保留所有故事，
And so you might say, let's use option 1 and keep all the stories,
但把论点移到故事 1 之后。
but move the thesis right after story 1.
也许你还会说你想加一个历史类比，
And also maybe say you want to add a historical analogy,
比如 Pixar 在 90 年代创作《Toy Story》，
Pixar creating Toy Story in the 90s,
这其实是一个非常鼓舞人心的故事，当时的 Pixar 还是一家小公司，
which is actually a really inspiring story where Pixar at that time, a small company,
却创作了《Toy Story》。
created Toy Story.
这是第一部完全由计算机动画制作的长片电影，而且只用了
Which was the first fully computer-animated feature-length film just using a very
一个很小的团队。基于你的反馈，AI 可能会给你一版修改后的大纲。
small team. Based on your feedback, the AI maybe gives you back a revised outline.
如果你对这个大纲满意，就可以让它扩展每个标题，
If you're satisfied with this outline, then you can tell it to expand each heading,
不是直接写成最终文本，而是先扩展成要点。
not even into the final text, but just into bullet points.
之后，你可能会决定就这些要点给它更多反馈
And following that, you might decide to give it more feedback on the bullet points
并在要点基础上迭代
and iterate on the bullet points
最后再让它生成文章正文。
before finally having it generate the text for the article.
事实证明，从大纲开始可以加快审阅速度。
And it turns out that starting with an outline speeds up review.
假设你正在写一篇有趣的文章，讨论飞鼠是否能携带
Let's say you're working on a fun article about whether a flying squirrel can carry
一颗椰子。相比让 AI 先和你一起处理大纲，
a coconut. In contrast to having AI first work with you on the outline,
再处理要点，最后生成最终文本，
then on bullet points and then on the final text.
也许你让 AI 从一开始就直接写最终文本。
Maybe you ask AI to write the final text right away, just from the start.
如果它写出这样的句子，
If it writes a sentence like this,
你可能会对其中几个词不满意，然后编辑几个词，
you may be unhappy with a few words and you can edit a few words,
但每次改动只改变一个词，
but changing each word just changes one word,
段落其余部分保持不变。
and the rest of the paragraph stays the same.
相比之下，如果你先写大纲，
In contrast, if you write an outline first
并且对大纲的某部分不满意，
and you're unhappy with part of the outline,
那么修改大纲会让最终文章中的整个部分——很多文字——
then changing the outline causes an entire section, that's a lot of words,
都发生改变。
of the final article to change.
所以这就是为什么编辑大纲，或与 AI 系统在大纲上迭代
So that's why editing the outline or iterating with the AI system on the outline is
是非常高效的做法，因为你可以想清楚如何只改大纲里的几个词，
very high leverage because you can figure out how to change just a few words in the
而这会让最终文章的一整段或一整节
outline and this will result in an entire paragraph or entire section of your final
都发生改变。而这一过程最终
article changing. And this ends
会成为你更高效地思考文章内容，
up being a much more efficient way for you to think through what you want to say in
并将其调整成你想要样子的方式。
an article and adapt it to what you want it to be.
根据 OpenAI 的数据，写作是 AI 最常见的用例之一。
Writing is one of the most common use cases of AI, according to OpenAI's data.
在以写作为主的对话中，大约三分之二是从一些已有的
Of the writing-focused chats, about two-thirds involve starting from some pre-
文本开始，而不是从零开始或从一张白纸
existing text rather than starting from scratch or starting from an empty sheet of
开始。当你已经有一些写好的内容时，
paper. When you already have something written up,
让 AI 为你提供批判性反馈并帮助你
it could be very helpful to have AI critique it for you and help you
把它改得更好，会非常有帮助。
make it better.
我们下个视频来看一些相关技巧。
Let's take a look at some techniques for this in the next video.
你经常会有一些想法，并已经围绕这些想法写了一些文本，
You often have some idea where you've already written some text about your idea,
但希望 AI 模型帮你编辑和润色文本。
but want an AI model to help you edit and refine your text.
我经常把我的写作拿给 AI，让它帮我改进。
I often show my writing to AI to help me make it better.
AI 非常擅长这项任务，而且它总有时间阅读你的内容，
AI is great at this task, and it always has time to read your work,
而找人帮忙可能没那么容易。
whereas finding a human to help you out might be trickier.
你已经学过如何避免迎合倾向，
You've already learned how to avoid sycophancy,
但怎样才能获得高质量的编辑建议和批判性反馈？
but how do you get the best quality editing and critique?
我们来看看。
Let's take a look.
用 AI 进行编辑的一个实用技巧，是逐段编辑文章，
One useful technique for editing with AI is to edit your article piece by piece,
比如一次一句，或一次一段，
such as one sentence at a time or one paragraph at a time,
而不是让它一次性编辑整篇文章，
rather than telling it to edit the entire article all at once
并围绕每一段做一点头脑风暴。
and to do a little bit of brainstorming around each paragraph.
直到我把某一段确定下来，再继续下一段。
Until I've nailed down one paragraph before going on to the next one.
例如，如果有人写下这样一个句子：公众认为实现 AGI，
For example, if someone's written this sentence, the public thinks achieving AGI,
也就是通用人工智能，意味着计算机将像人类一样聪明。
artificial general intelligence, means computers will be as smart as people.
你可以让 AI 帮你头脑风暴几种不同的表达方式。
You might ask AI to help brainstorm a few different ways to say this.
于是它可能会给出一种简洁有力的说法、一种有远见的说法、
And so it may come up with a punchy way to say this, a visionary way to say this,
一种口语化的说法。
a conversational way to say this.
根据你的编辑目标，
And depending on your editing goals,
你还可以再迭代几次，
you could even iterate a little bit
直到你为这段文字选出一个你喜欢的改写版本。
until you pick some version of rephrasing this part of the text that you like.
在你确定这一句之后，再继续第二句，或者第二
After you've nailed this down, then go on to the second sentence or maybe the second
段，和 AI 一起打磨这一小部分，
paragraph and work on that little bit with the AI
然后再继续下一句、下一段，依此类推，
and then go on to the next sentence and next paragraph and so on
直到处理完整篇文章。
until you get through your entire article.
我发现，一次处理长文章中的一小部分，
And I find that working on one piece of a long article at a time makes for a much
比让它同时改动大量内容更易于管理；
more manageable workflow than if it were to change a lot of things all at the same
否则你还要阅读这篇修改后的长文，弄清楚
time and then you're reading this very long edited article to figure out what has
哪里变了，哪些你喜欢、哪些不喜欢。
changed and what you like and don't like.
现在，如果你想对整篇已写好的内容获得更高层次、更整体的反馈，
Now, if you want high level, more holistic feedback about an entire piece,
事实证明 AI 也能在这方面帮上忙。
you've written, it turns out AI can help with that too.
但由于迎合倾向，AI 往往不是一个很客观的评论者。
But because of sycophancy, AI is often not a very good objective critic.
例如，你写了一篇关于宇航员走出飞船的科幻短篇故事。
For example, if you wrote a sci-fi short story about an astronaut stepping out of his ship.
如果你不附加进一步说明，直接让 AI 评审，
And if you ask AI without further instructions to critique it,
它很有可能会告诉你，你的作品非常出色。
there's a good chance it'll tell you whatever you did is fantastic work.
相比之下，有一个非常有用的技巧，可以引导 AI 如何评估你的
In contrast, there's a very helpful technique to guide AI in how to evaluate your
作品，从而给你更有价值的批判性反馈。
work to give you more helpful critical feedback.
那就是给它一个评分标准，也就是打分依据。
And that is to give it a rubric, and that means a grading criteria.
例如，你可以写一个评分标准，
For example, you might write a rubric
明确说明评判作品时最重要的标准是什么，
that specifies what are the most important criteria by
也就是用哪些标准来打分或评判作品。
which to grade or to judge the work.
比如你可以设定，故事中的角色占 25 分（满分 100 分），
So you may say that characters of the story is worth 25 points out of a hundred, and
情节占 25 分，世界观构建、写作，
plot, 25 points, world building, writing,
技巧，并建立一个评分体系；
craft and establish a point system
然后还要为如何评估每项标准制定详细说明。
and then also develop detailed instructions on how to evaluate each of these criteria.
比如在评估角色时，可以问每个有名字的角色是否都有目标，
So to evaluate characters, maybe ask if every named character has a goal and
这占 10 分；两个角色的目标之间是否有冲突，等等。
that's worth 10 points, conflict between two characters' goals and so on.
给 AI 非常明确的评判标准，会迫使它更客观。
And giving AI very explicit criteria on how to judge work forces the AI to be more objective.
这些标准有一点值得注意：每一项都被定义得非常清楚、
One thing to notice about these criteria is that each of them is very clearly
而且没有歧义。
and unambiguously defined.
因此对于每段文本，每一项标准要么为真要么为假，是或否，
So for each text, each of these criteria is either true or false, yes or no.
没有中间状态。
And there's nothing in between.
所以“每个有名字的角色都有目标”要么为真，要么不为真。
So either it's true that every named character has a goal or it's not true.
这些完全客观的标准会迫使 AI 审视你提供的任何内容，
And these completely objective criteria forces AI to look at whatever you're giving
并以客观、明确、无歧义的标准来衡量。
it through an objective, well-specified standard with no ambiguity.
顺便说一句，如果你不确定该使用什么样的评分标准，
And by the way, if you're not sure what rubric or what grading criteria to use,
你可以和 AI 一起头脑风暴，制定这个评分标准。
you can brainstorm with AI to develop that rubric.
而 AI 实际上很擅长这件事。
And AI is actually pretty good at this.
然后，在你写出评分标准之后，
And after you've written a rubric,
你可以把评分标准和故事一起提供给 AI。
you can then provide the rubric as well as the story.
在提示词中，要求 AI 保持客观。
And in your prompt, ask the AI to be objective.
比如：评审所附的科幻短篇故事，为每个类别打分，
So critique the attached sci-fi short story, assign a score per category,
最后把分数加起来。
then sum the scores at the end.
通过给 AI 这样非常明确的指令，让它最后把分数相加，
And by giving the AI these very clear instructions on what to do to sum the scores
它就有望对你的故事给出更客观的评估。
at the end, it then hopefully gives a more objective assessment of your story.
如果你愿意，也可以让它接着给出如何改进这个……的建议。
If you want, you can also ask it to then give you suggestions on how to improve the
故事，要在这份评分标准上做得更好，
story, to do better on this rubric,
这会让它给你更聚焦的建议，从而在
and this will cause it to give you more focused suggestions to improve it in the
你认为最重要的维度上改进。
dimensions that you think matter the most.
相反，写得不好的评分标准会鼓励迎合倾向
In contrast, poorly written rubrics encourage sycophancy
以及模糊或不够客观的思考。
and ambiguous or less objective thinking.
例如，如果你说：我写了一个科幻故事，请按 100 分制打分。
For example, if you say, I've worked on a sci-fi story, please score it out of 100.
这个提示词有一个奇怪之处：你先让它按 100 分制打分。
One of the things that's strange about this prompt is you first ask it to score out of 100.
这往往会促使它直接跳到结论，给出一个分数。
So that will tend to cause it to leap to a conclusion about what score.
然后才按类别打分：角色、情节、
And then only after that assign a score per category: characters, plot,
世界观构建和写作技巧。
world building, and writing craft.
而这些类别定义得很模糊，
And these are ambiguously defined categories
因为我们没有告诉它如何给角色、情节等打分。
because we've not told it how to score characters, plot, and so on.
因此，这往往会促使 AI 模型先给出一个分数，
And so this will tend to cause the AI model to first come up with some score
然后再去证明它，而不是先按照评分标准仔细评分，
and then justify it rather than score it carefully according to the rubric
再汇总得出一个更周到的分数。
and then add it up to then come up with a more thoughtful score.
或者，正如你在本模块末尾的练习实验中会看到的那样，
Or, as you see in the practice lab to come at the end of this module,
这类评分标准往往会给出比更客观的评分标准更高的分数。
this type of rubric will tend to give higher scores than more objective rubrics.
我们已经讨论过用 AI 进行批判性反馈，
We've talked about using AI to critique
并帮助提出改进作品的建议。
and help give suggestions for improving your work.
事实证明，让 AI 批判性地评审自己的作品，或让一个 AI 模型评审
It turns out that having AI critique its own work or having one AI model critique a
另一个 AI 模型的作品，也有助于改进结果。
different AI model's work can also help improve the results.
例如，如果你让 ChatGPT 为一款高级角色扮演
For example, if you ask ChatGPT to write a user manual for a fancy role-playing
游戏编写用户手册，它可能会为你生成一个文件。
game, then it might generate a file for you
你可以做的一件事是给 ChatGPT 一份评分标准，让它批判性地评审自己的作品。
and one thing you could do is provide a rubric for ChatGPT to critique his own work.
但一个巧妙的技巧是找一个不同的 AI 模型，
But a neat technique is to find a different AI model,
比如 Gemini，然后给它一个评分标准，让 Gemini 批判性地评审
maybe Gemini, and give that a grading rubric to have Gemini critique
ChatGPT 的作品，或反过来。
ChatGPT's work or vice versa.
事实证明，这种跨模型评审，
And it turns out that this type of cross-model review,
即让一个模型评审另一个模型的输出，
where you have one model review a different model's output,
有助于整合两个不同模型的一点知识，
it helps integrate a bit of knowledge from the two different models
并且可能产生比
and can result in slightly better results than
让一个模型评审它自己的结果稍微更好的效果。
if you were to ask one model to critique its own results.
我认为在这种情况下使用多个模型
I think using multiple models in this context
可能只会带来轻微的提升。
might give only a slight boost in performance.
实际上，如果你让 ChatGPT 评审它自己的结果，或让 Gemini 评审
Realistically, if you ask ChatGPT to review his own results or ask Gemini to review
它自己的结果，我认为也完全可以。
his own results, I think that will actually do just fine.
但有时我觉得让人放心的是，
But sometimes I find it reassuring
由一个完全不同的模型来评判另一个 AI 模型的输出。
if a totally different model judges the output of a different AI model.
我自己很少使用这种技巧。
And I use this technique only rarely myself.
但我确实会做的一件事是经常在不同的 AI 模型之间切换。
But one thing I do do is frequently switch between different AI models.
事实证明，AI 模型正在快速发展。
It turns out that AI models are advancing rapidly.
而在不同的时间点，不同模型在不同任务上的表现会更好。
And at different moments in time, different models will do better on different tasks.
因此，定期尝试不同模型可以帮助你保持敏锐，
And so routinely trying out different models will help keep you sharp
并不断磨练你对哪种模型最适合哪项任务的直觉。
and keep honing your intuition about what model is best for what task.
AI 模型具有所谓的锯齿状智能。
AI models have what's called jagged intelligence.
如果这个圆代表人们能做的任务，
If the circle represents the tasks that people can do,
可能是在工作中，也可能是在个人情境中，
maybe in a job or maybe in a personal context,
事实证明，AI 可以在某些事情上做得比任何人都好，
it turns out that AI can do some things better than any person,
比如快速阅读大量网页或解决棘手的数学问题。
like quickly read tons of web pages or solve tricky math problems.
但也有很多任务 AI 做得不如人类好。
But there are also many tasks that AI doesn't do as well as people.
所以有些任务 AI 表现不如人类，
So there are some tasks where AI does poorer than humans
而有些任务则比人类做得好得多。
and some where it does much better than humans.
不同的 AI 模型在不同方面呈现锯齿状。
And different AI models are jagged in different ways.
因此，不同 AI 模型擅长做的任务也不同。
So the tasks different AI models can do well are different.
此外，AI 模型市场竞争非常激烈。
Moreover, the marketplace of AI models is highly competitive.
所以 ChatGPT、Claude、Gemini，还有一长串模型提供商都在发布
So ChatGPT, Claude, Gemini, really a long list of model providers are releasing
更好的模型。
better models all the time.
因此，最适合你任务的模型可能会随着时间快速变化。
And so the best model for your task will likely change rapidly over time.
所以我发现我经常会把同一个提示词
And so I find that I'll often take the same prompt
同时输入给多个不同的模型，看看它们的表现如何。
and feed it to multiple different models to see how they compare.
这也在不断提升我的判断力，让我了解哪些模型最适合
And this continuously hones my intuition about what models are best for
我关心的哪些任务。
which of the tasks I care about.
这样我们就差不多到了本模块的结尾。
So that takes us to almost the end of this module.
我希望你已经看到，AI 模型在推理任务上也非常有用，
I hope you've seen that AI models are really useful for reasoning tasks as well
在头脑风暴、写作、编辑和批判性反馈你的工作方面也是如此。
as for brainstorming, writing, editing and critiquing your work.
这些都是把 AI 作为思考伙伴的强大方式，
These are powerful ways of using AI as a thought partner
我在自己的工作中发现它们非常有用，相信你也会。
that I found very useful in my own work and that I'm confident you will too.
让我们进入下一个视频，探索本模块的实践实验。
Let's go on to the next video to explore the practice lab for this module.
我希望你练习我们讨论过的、使用 AI 的技巧，
I hope you practice the techniques we talked about for using AI
在接下来的实践实验中把 AI 作为思考伙伴。
as a thought partner in the upcoming practice lab.
你可以再次并排对比更有效
You can explore once again side by side more effective
和不太有效的头脑风暴与 AI 批判性反馈策略。
and less effective strategies for both brainstorming and AI critique.
我们来看一下。
Let's take a look.
同样，当实验弹出时，你可以关闭教程。
Once again, when the lab pops up, you can dismiss the tutorial.
你也可以在这里找到教程，
You can also find the tutorial here as well
以及我希望你在这里遵循的说明。
as the instructions I hope you follow over here.
这里的按钮与上一个实验类似，
And the buttons here, similar to the previous lab,
允许你输入不同的提示词来进行头脑风暴。
allow you to enter different prompts to brainstorm.
这里是一个上下文较少的提示词：我需要一份健身计划，30 岁，
Here is a prompt with less context: I need a workout plan, 30 years old,
想变得更强壮。
want to get stronger.
而这是一个更详细的提示词，带有更多有用的背景信息。
Whereas this is a more detailed prompt with more helpful context.
你可以像这样运行它，看看输出的差异。
And so you can run it like so and see the difference in the outputs.
让我聚焦这个更详细的示例。
So let me focus on this more detailed example.
右侧给出了方案 1，看起来相当合理，还有方案 2，
On the right, it's given a program 1, which looks pretty reasonable, and a program 2,
看起来也相当合理。
which also looks pretty reasonable.
我们还有一些建议的提示词，帮助你对它进行优化。
And we also have a few suggested prompts for how you might refine it.
也许我对这个感兴趣。
So maybe I'm drawn to this.
让我这样做，然后让它继续对话。
Let me do that and have it continue the conversation.
然后它会根据你对这些方案的反馈来优化结果。
Then it will take this feedback on the programs it has given you in order to refine its results.
顺便说一句，我自己就在使用 AI 帮我生成的健身计划，
By the way, I actually use a workout program that AI had helped me to generate,
并且我发现这在我的个人生活中很有帮助，帮助我理清日常健身计划。
and I've found this helpful in my personal life for thinking through my regular workout plan.
所以如果你喜欢健身，
And so if you're a fan of working out,
也许你也会发现它给出的一些建议很有用。
maybe you'll find some of the suggestions it makes useful as well.
我们回到主页。
Let's go back to the homepage.
这里还有几个头脑风暴提示词示例，其中一个是简单提示词：
Here are a couple more examples of brainstorming prompts with a simple prompt,
我有 1000 美元可以投资。
I have $1,000 to invest.
我该怎么做？与之相比，另一个提供了更多背景信息。然后，
What should I do versus giving more context. And then,
我应该考虑哪些选项？
What are some options I should consider?
希望你也能试试这个，
Hope you try this out as well,
以及一些批判性反馈科幻故事的示例，
as well as some examples of critiquing a sci-fi story
而右侧是一个客观评分标准的示例。
and this is an example of an objective rubric on the right.
我希望你打开它并通读一遍，让自己了解一个
And I hope you bring this up and read through it to give yourself a sense of what a
写得很好的客观评分标准是什么样。
well-written objective rubric looks like.
将其与一个更主观的评分标准进行对比。
Compare that with what a more subjective rubric looks like.
如果点击 compare，你会看到这些评审质量的差异。
And if you hit compare, you see the difference in the quality of these reviews.
事实上，也许并不意外，使用较不客观的评分标准时，
And in fact, maybe not surprisingly, with the less objective rubric,
它得 83 分（满分 100）。
it gets 83 out of 100.
但更客观的评分标准下，是 75 分（满分 100）。
But the more objective rubric, 75 out of 100.
它还会给出更有帮助的建议，告诉你如何改进你的故事。
It also gives more helpful suggestions on how to improve your story.
除了批判性反馈和改进科幻故事，
In addition to critiquing and improving a sci-fi story,
你还可以看看这些示例，帮助你改进求职信，
you can also take a look at these examples of helping you improve a cover letter for
用于申请工作，以及批判性反馈
applying for a job as well as critique
并帮助你改进一个可能的商业计划
and help you to improve a possible business plan
在查看完这五个示例之后。
after checking out these five examples.
也请尝试你自己的提示词，或你自己的故事、求职信或
Please also try your own prompts or try your own stories or cover letters or
商业计划或其他内容。
business plans or something else.
我鼓励你使用这个界面去尝试不同的头脑风暴方式
And I encourage you to use this interface to play with different ways to brainstorm
或批判性反馈你的写作。
or to critique your writing.
本模块就到这里。
So that's it for this module.
请尽情探索这个实验。
Please enjoy exploring the lab.
接下来，我们进入最后一个模块，你会看到文本之外的应用。
Next, let's go on to the final module where you see applications beyond text.
具体来说，你会学习多模态提示，也就是
Specifically, you look at multimodal prompting in
让你的 AI 同时使用图像和音频
which you get your AI to also use images and audio
还会学习构建像游戏这样的应用。
and also look at building applications like games.
这会非常有趣。
It'll be a lot of fun.
我们看到的其中一个例子会和烟花有关，所以
And one of the examples we see will have something to do with fireworks, so
到时见。
I'll see you there.
在前两个模块中，我们主要让 AI 生成文本，
In the previous two modules, we've mostly had AI generate text,
但 AI 也能生成更丰富的输出类型，比如图像、视频等等。
but AI can produce richer types of outputs as well, like images, videos and so on.
我们把这些称为多模态输出，也就是包含多种模态的输出。
We call these multimodal outputs, that is outputs with multiple modalities.
针对多模态输出进行提示会有些不同，
Prompting for multimodal output is a bit different
因为多模态交互更慢、成本也更高。
because multimodal interactions are slower and more costly.
但这些能力会让你用 AI 完成更多事情。
But these capabilities will let you get a lot more done with AI.
此外，我们还会学习多模态输入，
Additionally, we'll also look at multimodal inputs,
具体来说，如果你想给 AI 展示一些图像并让它进行推理。
specifically if you want to show some images to your AI and have it reason about that.
我们开始吧。
Let's dive in.
AI 模型可以生成图像、视频、语音，甚至音乐、代码等等。
AI models can generate images, videos, voices, even music, code, and more.
你可能已经见过 AI 生成各种有趣、富有创意的图像。
You might have seen AI generate various fun, creative images.
我想和大家分享一个我非常喜欢的 AI 图像生成例子。
I want to share with you one example of AI image generation that I really enjoyed.
在我女儿 Nova 7 岁生日时，
For my daughter Nova's 7th birthday,
我想要一个独特的蛋糕设计，而她很喜欢猫。
I wanted a unique cake design and she loves cats.
于是我们用 AI 图像生成来探索不同的蛋糕设计。
So we used AI image generation to explore different cake designs.
这里最左边的图像是一张 AI 生成的图片，使用一款 AI 生成
The leftmost image here is an AI generated image created with an AI generation
软件 Nano Banana 制作，它由 Google 开发。
software called Nano Banana, which is created by Google.
而这是我女儿非常喜欢的一张图。
And this is a picture that my daughter really liked.
她想要一个和这张生成图像一样的蛋糕。
She wanted a cake that looks like this generated image.
然后我们把这张图拿给一位烘焙师看，
We then took the image and showed it to a baker
请烘焙师把这张图做成一个真实的 3D 蛋糕。
and asked the baker to render this picture into a real-life 3D cake.
右边的照片显示我女儿正在切这个她很喜欢的生日蛋糕。
And the picture on the right shows my daughter cutting this birthday cake that she loved.
所以在这个例子里，图像生成最终成了一个头脑风暴工具，用来探索
So in this case, image generation wound up being a brainstorming tool to explore
不同的蛋糕设计，直到我们找到一个能做成真实 3D 蛋糕的方案，
different cake designs until we found one that turned into a real-life 3D cake
最后我们都吃了，而且很喜欢。
that we all ate and liked.
除了生成图像之外，
In addition to generating images,
我也很喜欢用 AI 玩视频生成。
I really enjoy playing with AI for video generation as well.
这是我们团队生成的一个有趣视频，里面一个男人在缩小。
Here's a fun video generated by our team of a man shrinking.
这种视频以前可能需要昂贵的特效，
That video would previously have required maybe expensive special effects,
但现在 AI 直接就能生成。
but now AI can just generate it.
AI 还可以生成语音。
AI can also generate voices.
这是我的声音克隆在朗读 The Batch 中的一封信，
Here's a voice clone of me reading out loud a letter from The Batch,
The Batch 是 DeepLearning.AI 每周发布的新闻通讯，介绍 AI 领域的重要动态。
which is a weekly newsletter that DeepLearning.AI publishes to cover what matters in AI.
亲爱的朋友们，这是本周 The Batch 的最新内容，
Dear friends, here's the latest from this week's issue of The Batch,
生成式 AI 更快进展的一个障碍是评估，也就是 evals，
a barrier to faster progress in generative AI is evaluations, evals,
尤其是针对生成自由文本的自定义 AI 应用的评估。
particularly of custom AI applications that generate free-form text.
顺便说一下，我给我的父母都播放过我声音克隆的音频，
By the way, I've played audio of my voice clone to both of my parents
结果其中一位家长能听出那不是我自己，
and it turns out one of my parents could tell it wasn't me
另一位家长分不清那是我还是我的声音克隆。
and one of my parents could not tell if it was me or my voice clone.
为了不给自己惹麻烦，
And to avoid me getting into trouble,
我不会透露是哪位家长听错了。
I will not reveal which of my parents got it wrong.
但我认为声音克隆已经做得非常好了。
But I think voice clones are getting really good.
最后，AI 还可以生成代码。
Lastly, AI can generate code.
我之前提到我女儿喜欢猫，她还喜欢黄色。
I mentioned my daughter loves cats. She also loves the color yellow.
所以当她老师提到
And so when her teacher mentioned
希望班里的孩子用键盘打字能再快一点时，
that she wished kids in the class could type on a keyboard a little bit faster,
我用 AI 生成了这个打字游戏：如果我女儿敲对了字母，
I used AI to generate this typing game, where if my daughter hits the right letter,
她就会看到一段有趣的动画——一只猫被喂食，她非常喜欢。
Then she sees this fun little animation of a cat being fed, which she loves.
用 AI 写代码让这件事对每个人都更简单、更容易上手，
Using AI to write code has made it easier and more accessible for everyone,
包括你，只要你想写至少一些基础的计算机程序。
including you, if you wish to write at least basic computer programs.
稍后我会在本模块中进一步讲解，当你使用 AI 模型时，
I'll say more about this later in this module, when you're working with AI models,
你可以使用多种输入和输出类型的组合。
there are many combinations you can use of input and output types.
例如，你可以输入文本和图像，比如
For example, you can input text and images, such as
如果你输入一张像这样的灵感图片，
if you input an inspirational image like this,
如果你喜欢这套万圣节服装，以及这个计划——我的万圣节装扮。
if you like this Halloween costume and also the plan, my Halloween costume.
在这种情况下，AI 模型可能会输出一段文字说，
And in this case, the AI model might output text that says,
让我帮你头脑风暴几个外星人风格的服装创意。
let me help you brainstorm a few alien-inspired costume ideas.
或者你也可以把音乐上传给 AI 模型
Or you can also upload music to an AI model
让它帮我规划我的鬼屋，而 AI 也许可以把这些内容
and ask it to help me plan my haunted house and AI may be able to take these things
作为输入，生成文字和一段鬼屋设计视频，并融入
as input and generate both text and a video of a haunted house design incorporating
你那些令人毛骨悚然的声音。
your creepy sounds.
音频。
Audio.
AI 模型可以相对轻松地使用这些输入类型中的大多数。
AI models can use most of these input types relatively easily.
有些类型作为输入使用会稍微更贵或成本略高，
Some are slightly more expensive or slightly more costly to use as an input,
但这些差异并不是很大。
but the differences aren't very significant.
相比之下，生成不同类型输出所需的时间和成本差异很大。
In contrast, the time and cost of generating different types of output vary significantly.
特别是，有些数据类型要慢得多
In particular, some data types are much slower
而且生成成本比其他类型高得多。
and much more costly to generate than others.
给你一个大致的印象，文本在生成时间或成本上往往处于较低的一端。
To give you a sense, text tends to be on the lower end in terms of time or cost of generation.
所以 AI 生成文本非常高效。
So AI is very efficient at generating text.
事实上，现代 AI 始于大型语言模型，有时缩写为 LLMs。
In fact, modern AI has started with large language models, sometimes abbreviated LLMs.
但正因为它们是从语言起步的，
But because they started with language,
许多模型确实被调整来处理文本。
a lot of them were really adapted to deal with text.
而且它在这方面非常高效。
And it's very efficient at that.
生成语音往往会更贵一些
Generating speech tends to be a bit more expensive
生成图像还要更贵，而生成视频则要贵得多得多，
and generating images even more expensive and generating video much, much,
比图像或任何其他模态都要贵得多。
much more expensive than images or any of the other modalities.
我们越往这张图的右边走，
And the further we go to the right of this chart,
生成单个输出所需的时间就越长
the longer it takes or the more time it takes to generate a single output
而且这样做的成本也越高。
and also the more costly it is to do so.
过去几年，图像生成取得了显著进步。
Image generation has progressed significantly in the last few years.
这是 Imagen 在 2022 年生成的一段短视频，
Here's a short video generated by Imagen, which was in 2022,
它是 Google 当时最先进的模型。
a state-of-the-art model by Google.
它看起来很不错，但仍有一些人工痕迹。
And it looks pretty good but still has some artificial-looking artifacts.
背景墙上的线条不太对。碗碟在清洗过程中还变了样子。
The lines weren't quite right on the back wall. The dishes changed mid-wash.
相比之下，现代 AI 视频生成看起来好得多
In contrast, modern AI video generation looks much better
而且还可以与生成的音频自动同步。
and can also be synchronized automatically with generated audio.
AI 语音生成也已经进步了很多。
AI voice generation has also gotten much better.
这是 AI 几年前能做的事情。
Here's what AI could do. Just a few years ago.
但在你开始调整任何东西之前，你需要先定义成功是什么样子。
But before you start tuning anything, you need to define what success looks like.
这一步很容易被忽略，但它很基础。
This step is easy to overlook, but it's foundational.
它听起来有点机械，表现力不强。
It sounded a bit robotic, not that expressive.
相比之下，现代 AI 语音生成听起来可以更有表现力
In contrast, modern AI voice generation can sound much more expressive
也更自然。
and much more natural.
但在你开始调整任何东西之前，你需要先定义成功是什么样子。
But before you start tuning anything, you need to define what success looks like.
这一步很容易被忽略，但它很基础
This step is easy to overlook, but it's foundational
尤其是在你生成多模态数据时。
if you're generating multimodal data.
你之前学到的一些技巧，
Some of the techniques you learned earlier,
比如给模型足够的上下文，或者使用可用的最佳模型。
such as giving the model enough context and maybe using the best model available.
这些技巧应用于多模态生成也比较容易。
Those are relatively easy techniques to apply as well to multimodal generation.
但其他一些技巧，比如生成多个选项，
But some of the other techniques like generating multiple options,
你仍然可以这样做。
you can still do that.
但如果每个选项现在都需要很多秒甚至几分钟来生成，
But if each option now takes many seconds or even a few minutes to generate,
那么这就变得更难应用，因为最终你不得不等待很长时间。
then this becomes harder to apply because you end up having to wait for a long time.
或者如果你想迭代许多设计，
Or if you want to iterate through many designs,
那么如果每次生成都很耗时或成本很高，这也会变得更困难。
then that too becomes harder if each generation takes a long time or is costly.
但如果你有耐心多等一会儿，
But if you have the patience to wait a little bit longer,
那么所有这些技巧也同样适用于生成音频、图像、视频等。
then all of those techniques also apply to generating audio, images, video and so on.
能力越大，责任越大，
With great power comes great responsibility,
AI 技术既可以用于善，也可以用于恶。
and AI technologies can be used for good or for harm.
以语音生成为例。
Take voice generation.
如果你录制了一个播客，想做一点小修正，
If you have recorded a podcast and you want to make little fixes,
如今使用 AI 语音生成就可以很方便地完成，只需……
that can be quite conveniently done today using AI voice generation to just
重新合成你可能说错的一两个词。
resynthesize one or two words that you may have flubbed.
或者如果你在制作视频游戏，想给角色赋予逼真的声音，
Or if you're building a video game and you want to give characters lifelike voices,
越来越多的视频游戏设计师正在使用 AI 语音生成来实现这一点。
more and more video game designers are using AI voice generation to do so.
这确实引发了关于配音演员生计的重要问题。
It does raise important questions about the livelihoods of voice actors.
我也同情所有配音演员
And I sympathize with all the voice actors
他们对 AI 语音生成感到担忧。
that are worried about AI voice generation.
与此同时，我认为同样很有价值的是
At the same time, I think it's also very valuable
AI 语音生成让更多人可以更容易地构建
that AI voice generation is making it easier for a lot more people to build
好玩的视频游戏，包括那些开发者
entertaining video games, including developers
他们无法接触到优秀配音演员。
that don't have access to the great voice actors.
与这些应用相比，也有一些明显有害的用途。
In contrast to these applications, there are also some that are clearly harmful.
不幸的是，诈骗正在增多
Unfortunately, there's been a rise of scams
有人会使用 AI 语音克隆来冒充他人，
where someone would use an AI voice clone to pretend to be someone else,
可能是假装某人的亲属遇到紧急情况
to maybe pretend that someone's relative is in an emergency
并要求紧急汇款。
and to ask to wire emergency funds.
AI 有益用例的数量远远超过有害用例。
The number of beneficial use cases of AI vastly outnumbers the number of harmful ones.
但我们仍需努力打击有害应用。
But we still have work to do to combat the harmful applications.
我希望我们每个人都只将这些技术用于有益
And I hope that each of us will only use these techniques for beneficial
且负责任的用途。
and responsible applications.
正如你所见，AI 现在能处理的远不止文本。
So as you've seen, AI can now work with much more than text.
它可以处理图像、音频、视频、代码等等。
It can work with images, audio, video, code and more.
你学到的大多数提示技巧
And most of the prompting techniques you learned
到目前为止都将有助于处理多模态输入和输出。
so far will be helpful for handling multimodal inputs and outputs.
一个特别有用的能力是给 AI 图像作为输入
One especially useful capability is giving AI images as input
这样它们就能看到你在说什么。
so they can see what you're talking about.
我们继续看下一个视频，了解如何在提示中使用图像。
Let's go on to the next video to see how to use images in your prompts.
在提示中提供图像可以丰富 AI 的上下文背景。
Providing images in your prompt can enrich the context for the AI.
你想让 AI 看到的东西的图片、手写文本的图片，
Pictures of something you want the AI to see, pictures of handwritten text,
任何可能难以用语言描述的东西。
really anything that might be hard to describe in words?
这个视频将帮助你建立对 AI 能在图像中看到什么的直觉。
This video will help you build intuition about what AI can see in images.
这是我在白板前讲解一些 AI 概念的照片。
Here's a picture of me explaining some concepts in AI in front of a whiteboard.
我的字写得不是很好，
My handwriting is not that great,
而且有不少数学概念
and there are a number of math concepts
我正尝试在这块白板上说明。
that I'm trying to illustrate on this whiteboard.
如果你把这张图片上传到 AI 模型并问：“这节课是关于什么的”，
If you upload this picture to an AI model and ask, what is this class about,
它可能会输出类似这样的内容。
it may output something like this.
他在教卷积神经网络。
He's teaching a convolutional neural network.
有趣的是，我的头挡住了“卷积”这个词，
And the neat thing is my head is blocking the word convolutional,
但它从这张图片中判断出来了。
but it knows from this picture.
所以我在教的是一种叫做卷积神经网络的特定 AI 技术，
So I'm teaching about a specific AI technique called a convolutional neural network,
它提取了关于我正在画的内容的一些事实
and it's extracted some facts about what I'm drawing
并且很好地猜测了我接下来可能让学生做什么。
and also has some good guesses about what I might ask students to do next.
所以它能对这幅图像做出相当聪明的解读。
So it's able to make a pretty smart interpretation of this image.
AI 模型观察图像时的一个弱点是，它们倾向于看
One weakness of AI models in terms of how they look at images is they tend to look
图像的大致内容，但可能漏掉细粒度细节。
at the coarse image, but may miss fine-grained details.
例如，如果你把这张图片上传到 AI 模型并问：
So for example, if you upload this picture to an AI model and ask,
我健身房里的这些器械是什么？
what are these machines at my gym?
它可能会非常自信地给出类似这样的答案，但结果却是错误的。
It may confidently give an answer like this, which turns out to be wrong.
这是因为很多健身器械，
And that's because a lot of gym machines,
如果你透过稍微模糊的镜头看它们，
if you look at them through a slightly blurry lens,
它们看起来都有点相似。
they all look a little bit similar.
如今 AI 还不太擅长观察图像的细节，
And AI is not that good today at looking at the fine details of images to
来区分臀肌后踢机还是腿弯举机。
distinguish what really is a glute kickback machine or a hamstring curl machine.
相比之下，如果你上传像这样的图片
In contrast, if you were to upload an image like this
并要求它为这个产品制作销售广告，
and ask it to create a sales ad for this item,
它实际上做得很好，因为这是一个视觉上非常独特的物体。
it actually does pretty well because this is a very visually distinct object.
所以即使你透过稍微模糊的镜头看这个，嗯，
And so if you're looking at this even through the slightly blurry lens, yeah,
你也能看出这是一个真人大小仓鼠轮跑步机。
you kind of see this is a human sized hamster wheel treadmill.
当你上传图像时，你也可以给它中等复杂度的指令
When you upload an image, you can also give it moderately complex instructions on
告诉它如何处理这张图像。
what to do with it.
所以上传这样一张收据后，你可以问它：我该付的那部分账单是多少？
So uploading a receipt like this, you can ask it, what's my portion of the bill?
我点了这些东西。在这个例子里，它算对了。
I had these items. And in this case, it gets it correct.
AI 读取这类文字的能力还不错，但确实会出错。
AI's ability to read text like this is not bad. It does make mistakes.
所以对于高风险场景，我不会信任它。
So I wouldn't trust it for high stakes applications.
但如果你想快速看一眼，
But if you want to take a quick look and
并且愿意花几秒钟再核对一下结果，
if you're willing to spend a few seconds to double check the result,
那么它能做得还不错。
then it could do decently well.
而且事实证明，AI 甚至很擅长读取手写文字。
And AI turns out to be pretty good at even reading handwritten text.
如果你把这样的图片上传给 AI，让它转录文字，
If you upload a picture like this to AI and ask it to transcribe it,
它做得相当不错。
it does a pretty decent job.
你也可以自己试着读一下这段草书手写文字，看看
Feel free if you want to try reading this cursive handwriting yourself to see
是否能比 AI 表现得更好。
if you can outperform the AI.
因此，如果你上传一张这样的图片并写下提示词，
And so if you upload an image like this and write a prompt,
比如“根据这些手写信件建立一个家族历史档案”，
like build an archive of a family's history based on these handwritten letters,
我不会完全信任它能逐字准确读取所有内容，
I wouldn't trust it to read everything completely accurately,
但它可能在合理时间内完成。用 AI 生成图像让我的生活变得更有趣了。
but it might take a reasonable amount of time. Generating images with AI has made my life more fun.
例如，我曾为我的孩子们使用图像生成。
For example, I've used image generation for my kids.
生日派对或制作有趣的插图。
Birthday parties or to make fun illustrations.
生成高质量 AI 图像是一项你可以学习的技能，
Generating high quality AI images is a skill you can learn
而了解 AI 图像生成器是如何训练的，将帮助你控制
and understanding how AI image generators were trained will help you to control
图像生成，以获得更好的输出。
image generation to get better outputs.
我们来看一看。
Let's take a look.
AI 图像生成的一个巧妙应用是，如果你输入一张图像
One neat application of AI image generation is if you input an image
并要求它编辑，右边是一张我童年的照片，
and ask it to edit it, this is a childhood picture of me on the right,
左边是我弟弟，中间是我们的一位儿时朋友。
my younger brother on the left and one of our childhood friends in the middle.
这是一张有些褪色的老照片。
And this is an old, somewhat faded image.
如果你把这张照片上传给 AI 模型，让它去除反光
And if you upload this to an AI model and ask it to remove the glare
和粗糙纹理，并调整为更自然的宽高比，
and the rough texture and to make it a more natural aspect ratio,
它就能生成这样的效果，看起来像一张修复得很好的照片。
it can produce something like this, which looks like a nicely restored photo.
这张图片的修复是用 Google 的 Nano Banana 模型完成的。
This particular image restoration was done with Google's Nano Banana model.
如果你不确定如何给 AI 图像生成系统写提示词，
If you're not sure how to prompt an AI image generation system,
实际上你可以让文本类 AI 模型帮你写提示词。
you can actually ask a text-based AI model to help you write a prompt.
例如，如果你让它生成一个图像提示词：一只猫秘密经营
For example, if you ask it to generate a prompt for an image of a cat secretly running
夜间咖啡店。
a coffee shop at night.
文本类 AI 模型可能会写出像这样的提示词。
An AI text model may write a prompt like this.
注意，这里它指定了场景、角色细节，
Notice that here it specifies a setting, specifies details of the character,
还指定了情绪或风格。
and specifies a mood or a style.
如果你不喜欢其中任何细节，都可以按自己的喜好修改。
And if you don't like any of these details, you can modify them to your liking.
而这样的提示词可能会生成右边这张可爱的图片。
And a prompt like this might generate this cute picture on the right.
擅长视觉艺术的人有一套描述图像的特定语言。
People skilled in the visual arts have a certain language for describing images.
例如，具有这种观感的图片称为“电影感”。
For example, a picture like this with this look is cinematic.
这是一张水彩风格图像。
This is a watercolor image.
这是一张赛博朋克风格图像，这是一张动漫风格图像。
This is a cyberpunk image and this is an anime image.
我发现艺术爱好者和艺术史爱好者特别擅长图像提示，
And I find that art buffs and art history buffs excel at image prompting
因为他们理解图像的语言，
because they understand the language of images
能比我们这些不懂这种语言的人用更精确的语言描述他们想要的画面，
and can describe what they want using more precise language than those of us
而我们找不到合适的词来描述
that don't know this language and can't quite find the right words to describe the
我们想要的那种画面。所以，如果你想
look that we want. So if you want.
真正成为图像生成的高手，
to become really expert at generating images,
可能值得去阅读或学习一些关于图像语言的知识，
it could be worth reading up or studying a little bit about the language of images
以了解如何准确描述不同的图像。
to understand how to accurately describe different images.
事实上，做到这一点的一个方法是把图像上传给 AI 模型，
And in fact, one way to do so would be to upload images to an AI model
然后问 AI 它会如何描述这些图像。
and ask the AI how it would describe those images.
这可以训练你的直觉，让你知道哪些词可以用来描述
And this could hone your instincts on what types of words can be used to describe
哪些类型的图像。
what types of images.
事实证明，图像生成使用的技术与文本生成非常不同。
It turns out image generation uses a very different technology than text generation.
当 AI 生成文本时，它是一块一块地产生输出。
When AI is generating text, it produces the output piece by piece.
也就是说，它一次生成几个字符。
So it generates a few characters at a time.
相比之下，在生成图像时，
In contrast, when generating an image,
它并不是一次只生成几个像素。
it doesn't generate the image a few pixels at a time.
它是整张图像一次性生成的。
It generates the entire image all at once.
具体来说，在训练过程中，也就是
Specifically during training, that is
当 AI 模型查看图片（可能是网上找到的图片），以学习
when an AI model is looking at pictures maybe found online in order to learn what
图像是什么样子。
images look like.
它通常会查看图像的说明文字或描述，
It will typically look at captions or descriptions of images,
比如“木桌上的一小盆盆栽”。
like a small potted plant on a wooden table.
它们会学习从一张看起来像纯噪声的图像开始。
And they'll learn to start from an image that looks like pure noise.
这只是一个随机像素值的网格，
This is just a grid of random pixel values,
然后它会学习逐步去除或减去图像中的噪声，从
and it will then learn to sequentially remove or subtract noise from the image to go
从右侧的纯噪声，到一张略微模糊的盆栽图片，再到不那么
from pure noise on the right to a slightly blurry picture of a potted plant to less
模糊的一张，再到更不模糊的一张。
blurry one, to less blurry one.
最终得到一张清晰的盆栽图片。
To finally a sharp picture of a potted plant.
这就是 AI 模型在训练中反复练习的过程。
And that's what the AI model tries to repeatedly practice doing during training.
实现这一过程的模型称为扩散模型。
A model that does this is called a diffusion model.
然后，当你使用它并写下提示词时，
Then when you come in and when you write a prompt,
比如生成一张桌上盆栽的图片，
maybe create an image of a potted plant on the table,
它就会经历这个过程，从一张纯噪声图像开始，
it then goes through this process starting from a pure noise image
然后逐步去除噪声，得到最终的图像。
and then gradually tries to remove noise from it to come up with that final image.
关键在于它如何学习减去噪声，以还原出
And the key is how it learns to subtract noise to maybe reveal the image
人心中可能设想的那张图像。
that the person might have had in mind.
扩散模型确实会生成随机输出
Diffusion models do generate random outputs
它们也可能产生某些类型的错误
and they can also make certain types of errors
如果你反复让 AI 模型生成盆栽，
if you repeatedly ask an AI model to generate a potted plant,
每次运行算法，可能会得到不同的图像，就像这里展示的这样。
different times you run the algorithm might result in different images like the one shown here.
但许多人还观察到
But many people have also observed
扩散模型往往会生成看起来很奇怪的手，
that the diffusion model tends to generate weird looking hands,
通常手指多于或少于五根，
often with more or fewer than five fingers,
而且经常输出乱码文字，比如这里的“happy birthday”拼写错得很厉害。
and it can often output garbled text like happy birthday is very badly misspelled here.
它还可能导致角色不一致。
And it can also lead to inconsistent characters.
因此，如果你让它生成一部卡通，
So if you ask it to generate a cartoon,
角色头发在这部卡通的两个画面之间发生了变化。
the character's hair has changed between the two frames of this cartoon.
幸运的是，现代 AI 模型在处理这些问题上已经进步很多。
Fortunately, modern AI models have become much better at addressing these problems.
例如，像 Nano Banana 这样的现代模型可以让你上传多篇
For example, modern models like Nano Banana can allow you to upload a number of
研究论文。
research papers.
让它生成一张信息图，它在文字处理上会做得相当不错
Ask it to generate an infographic and it'll do a decent job with text
文字看起来大多是合理的。
that looks mostly plausible.
或者如果你让它生成一部卡通，
Or if you ask it to generate a cartoon,
更现代的模型可以生成相当一致的角色，
the more modern models can generate fairly consistent characters,
这意味着现在这个角色，正如你所看到的，
meaning now this character, as you can see,
在这部卡通逐帧之间看起来非常相似。
looks very similar from frame to frame of this cartoon.
与文字生成相比，图中的文字看起来也相当不错。
And the text also looks pretty decent compared to text generation.
图像生成可能又慢又贵。
Image generation can be slow and costly.
例如，如果你只生成一小段文本，
For example, if you're generating just a short paragraph of text,
许多 AI 模型只需几秒钟就能完成，花费可能不到一美分。
many AI models can do that in just seconds and it may cost less than a cent.
当然，生成长段落文本，
Of course, generating long paragraphs of text,
或者让它长时间思考，成本会更高。
or if you ask it to think for a long time, that can cost more.
此外，AI 模型是一个词一个词，或者一次几个字符地生成内容的。
And also AI models generate word by word or maybe a few characters at a time.
如果你愿意，可以打断它或让它提前停止。
And you can interrupt it or have it stop early if you want.
相比之下，生成一张图像可能需要几十秒
In contrast, generating a single image might take tens of seconds
花费几美分，而且它是整张图像一次性生成。
and cost many cents, and it generates the image all at once.
而且通常没有提前停止的选项
And there often isn't an option to stop early
因为图像生成要昂贵得多。
because image generation is much more expensive.
这就是为什么我们在图像上迭代的能力通常更有限。
That's why our ability to iterate with images is usually more limited.
如果你要生成视频，那就更难了。
And if you're generating videos, then it gets even harder.
尽管有些内容生成起来更贵，
Even though some things are more expensive to generate,
好消息是，用 AI 生成几乎任何内容的成本都在下降。
the good news is the cost of generating virtually anything with AI is trending downward.
所以一年后，你为家里创作艺术或
So a year from now, it will be less expensive for you to create art for your home or
为家人的生日贺卡制作图案，都会比今天更便宜。
graphics for a family member's birthday card compared to today.
除了生成图像，AI 还可以帮你制作有趣的游戏
Beyond generating images, AI can also help you create fun games
和网站，而无需自己编写任何代码。
and websites without having to write any code yourself.
这是一种更进阶的能力，但仍很容易得到一些
This is a more advanced capability and it's still easy to get stuff
不工作的东西，或者让新手在尝试构建更复杂应用时卡住。
that doesn't work or for novices to get stuck trying to build more complex applications.
但我想让你初步体会一下，用 AI 构建定制软件是怎样工作的。
But I want to just give you a taste of how using AI to build custom software works.
虽然这没那么容易，但肯定比仅仅几个月前
While it's not that easy, it's also certainly much easier than it was just months
要容易得多，而且很可能比你以为的更简单。
ago and quite likely easier than you might think.
我们继续看下一个视频，了解如何用 AI 创建自己的小游戏或网站。
Let's go on to the next video to see how to use AI to create your own mini game or website.
构建电脑游戏和网站曾经是
Building computer games and websites used to be something
只有专业开发者才能做到的事情，
that only professional developers were able to do,
但通过编写文本提示词，这种能力正在变得大众化。
but the ability to do this is being democratized by writing text prompts.
你也能构建基础的软件应用和网站。
You, too, will be able to build basic software applications and websites.
这确实需要一些技巧，我不想让它听起来很轻松，
This does take some skill, and I don't want to make it sound trivial,
但在这一个视频里，你就能学到一些基础知识。
but in just this one video, you learn some of the basics.
这是一个非常令人兴奋的能力，我鼓励你去探索它。
This is a very exciting capability and I encourage you to explore it.
我见过很多不是软件工程师的人也玩得很开心。
I've seen many people who are not software engineers have a lot of fun with this.
即使只用一个提示词，也常常能做出一个很酷的小游戏或应用。
And even with just one prompt, it's often possible to get a cool little game or app.
我们来看一些使用这个提示词的例子，
Let's see some examples using this prompt,
构建一个游戏，让用户放置障碍物和目标，
build a game where the user has to place obstacles and a goal
然后它会模拟出你设计的内容。
and it creates a simulation of what you design.
Claude 生成了这个游戏，你可以玩，而且，你懂的，
Claude created this game, which you can play and it's, you know,
实际上相当酷。
actually pretty cool.
所以仅仅这样一个简短、简单的提示词，
So just a short, simple prompt like that,
领先的 AI 模型就能创建出相当有趣的游戏。
a leading AI model can create a reasonably interesting game.
你在练习实验中看到的一个例子是，提示 AI 模型生成
One example that you see in the practice lab is prompting an AI model to generate a
烟花展示。
fireworks display.
这是一个提示词，它创建了这个应用，
Here's a prompt, and this creates this app,
玩起来其实挺有趣的。
which is actually pretty fun to play with.
如果你正在尝试编写提示词，让 AI 为你构建一个简单的应用，
If you're trying to write a prompt to tell AI to build a simple app for you,
这里有一些你可以考虑写进提示词的构建要素。
here are some building blocks you might consider including in your prompt.
首先是明确你的目标，也就是你想创建什么。
First is to specify your goal for what you want to create.
其次，明确输入是什么，即用户需要向系统输入什么。
Next, specify what are the inputs, what the users need to input into the system.
最后，明确输出是什么，或者说应用向用户展示什么。
And then lastly, what are the outputs or what the app shows back to the user?
例如，在这个提示词中，我们告诉它
For example, in this prompt, we are telling it
它要生成一个有趣的烟花模拟器。
that it's going to generate a fun fireworks simulator.
输入是我想在屏幕上点击，输出是
The input is I want to click on the screen, and the output is,
看到五颜六色的烟花。
to see a colorful display of fireworks.
专业的开发者会用 AI 构建远比
Sophisticated developers will use AI to build much more complex applications than
我这里展示的复杂得多的应用，但这里只继续用更简单的例子。
what I'm showing here, but just to continue with the simpler examples.
要构建这样的游戏，你可以让它创建一个有趣的游戏，
To build a game like this, you might ask it to create a fun game
让用户放置障碍物和目标，
where the user has to place obstacles and a goal,
然后它会模拟出你设计的内容。
and it creates a simulation of what you design.
除了娱乐游戏之外，
In addition to entertaining games,
你还可以制作更有用、更实用的应用，
you can also make more useful and functional apps
它们能帮你节省时间或让生活更方便一点。
that help you save time or make your life a bit easier.
例如，你可以创建一个叫做番茄钟（Pomodoro timer）的工作计时器。
For example, you can create a work timer called a Pomodoro timer.
这是一种人们用来给工作或学习计时的计时器，
This is a type of timer that people use to time their work or studying,
每工作 25 分钟，穿插 5 分钟休息。
with 25 minutes of work interspersed with a 5-minute break.
或者你可以创建一个账单计算器。
Or maybe you can create a bill calculator.
在这里你可以输入账单金额，以及需要分摊账单的朋友人数，
Here you can input the bill and the number of friends you need to split the bill
应用会告诉你每个人应该付多少钱。
with, and the app can tell you how much each person should pay.
或者可以构建一个穿搭选择器应用，
Or maybe build an outfit picker app
帮你根据天气决定穿什么。
that helps you decide what to wear based on the weather.
这些应用每一个都能在日常生活中带来乐趣或实用价值。
Each of these apps could be fun or useful in everyday life.
如果你是刚接触用 AI 制作应用，它们也是很好的起点，
And they're also good starting points if you're new to making apps with AI
因为它们非常简单。
because they're quite simple.
特别是，每个应用都有一个明确且具体的任务。
In particular, they each have a specific well-defined task.
它们不需要任何额外的文件，
They also don't need any additional files
不需要上传任何文件，也不需要外部信息。
that need to be uploaded or outside information.
它们也是那种你可以打开、
And they're also something that you can open up,
用一小会儿然后关掉的东西。
use for a short period of time and then close.
如果你也想亲自尝试这样使用 AI，我鼓励你去实验。
If you're curious to try using AI this way yourself, I encourage you to experiment,
从构建简单应用开始。
starting with building simple apps.
事实证明，有些想法比其他想法更容易实现。
It turns out some ideas are easier to create than others.
例如，一个简单的平台游戏会相对容易构建，或者
others, for example, a simple platformer game would be relatively easier to build or
一个练习法语单词的测验。
a quiz to practice French words.
相比之下，在互联网上玩的多人游戏会难得多，
In contrast, a multiplayer game played over the internet that would be harder
也更复杂；或者带有 AI 反馈的实时法语练习也会更难构建。
and much more complex or live French practice with AI feedback will also be harder to build.
培养对 AI 容易构建什么的直觉需要一段时间，
It takes a while to hone intuition about what is easy for AI to build
以及什么是 AI 难以构建的。
and what is hard for AI to build.
如果你不确定，我鼓励你直接试一试。
If you're not sure, I encourage you to just try it out.
而最坏的情况不过是它不起作用，
And the worst thing that could happen is it doesn't work,
你也会开始培养对什么比较难的直觉。
and you start to hone your intuitions about what's hard.
但如果你刚开始尝试用 AI 构建应用，
But if you're just getting started trying to use AI to build apps,
我鼓励你从简单的想法开始，比如构建一个简单的游戏，然后看看
I encourage you to start with simple ideas like build a simple game and see
能否让 AI 把它做出来。
if you can get AI to do that.
等我们稍后进入本模块的实践实验时，
When we get to the practice lab later in this module,
你将能尝试几个只需一个提示就能构建的示例。
you'll be able to try a few examples that you can build with just a single prompt.
如果你想更深入地了解用 AI 构建软件，
If you want to dive deeper into using AI to build software,
我建议你参加 Build with Andrew 课程，
I encourage you to take the course Build with Andrew,
该课程由 DeepLearning.AI 提供。除了编写代码来构建游戏和网站，
offered by DeepLearning.AI. In addition to writing code to build games and websites.
AI 还可以帮助你分析数据，
AI can also help you to analyze data,
它可以通过编写代码来完成数据分析。
which it can do by writing code to do that data analysis.
同样，你不需要自己编写任何代码。
Again, you don't need to write any code yourself.
只需告诉 AI 你想要什么，它就会尝试为你编写代码。
Just tell AI what you want and it will try to write code to do it for you,
这可以在你的工作和个人生活中带来有用的洞察。
and this can lead to helpful insights in your work and personal life.
在下一个视频中，我们来看看如何使用 AI 进行数据分析。
In the next video, let's take a look at using AI for data analysis.
如果你有来自个人健康记录的数据，
If you have data from your personal health records,
比如你使用某个应用
like maybe if you use one of the apps
来跟踪你的心率或跑步时长，或者
that track your heart rate or running time or
你的数据是公司的销售记录，或者其他大多数类型的数据。
if your data is sales records from your company or really most other types of data.
比如你可能存储在电子表格中的数据，
Like what you might store in a spreadsheet table,
AI 很擅长编写代码来帮你分析这些数据，
AI can be pretty good at writing code to analyze this data for you
并尝试提取有用的洞察。
and to try to extract useful insights.
我们来看一些例子，希望能启发你尝试这个功能。
Let's look at some examples that I hope will inspire you to try out this capability.
如果你有可以下载到电子表格中的跑步追踪数据，
If you have running tracker data that you can download into a spreadsheet,
你可以尝试把那个电子表格上传到 AI 模型，并问它：
you might try uploading that spreadsheet to an AI model and asking it,
我的配速和距离进展如何？
how are my pace and distance progressing?
AI 系统可能会花一些时间编写代码来分析它，
And an AI system might spend some time to write some code to analyze it
也许还会为你生成图表。
and maybe generate a plot for you.
还可能提供一些洞察；或者如果你经营一家小企业，
And also potentially provide some insights or if you run a small business
并且你有一份销售数据的电子表格，
and you have a spreadsheet of sales data,
你可以上传那些数据并询问 AI 模型，
you can upload that data and ask the AI model,
关于这个月的销售，你能告诉我什么？
what can you tell me about this month's sales?
AI 可能会分析一会儿，
The AI could analyze for a little while
它可能真的会编写一些代码来做比如计算月度收入，
and it might actually write some code to do things like compute the monthly revenue
或者创建图表，并尝试向你展示它发现的任何洞察。
or to create a graph and try to show you whatever insights it finds.
我发现 AI 的数据分析通常不如一位真正
I find that AI data analysis often isn't as sophisticated as a really,
真正优秀的人类数据科学家。
really good human data scientist.
但在提取基本洞察并高效完成方面，
But for pulling out basic insights and doing so efficiently,
AI 模型可以相当出色。
an AI model can be pretty good.
AI 模型是如何编写和执行代码的？
How do AI models write and execute code?
事实证明，它的底层工作方式是，
It turns out that the way it works under the hood,
编写和执行或运行代码的能力，就像任何其他工具一样
the ability to write and execute or to run code is like any other tool
是 AI 模型可能使用的工具。
that the AI model might use.
你已经见过 AI 模型如何拥有工具来执行联网搜索，或读取
You've seen how an AI model might have tools to carry out web search or to read
和写入文件等等。
and write files and so on.
而且一些 AI 模型还有运行计算机程序或运行代码的工具。
And some AI models also have a tool to run a computer program or to run code.
这种能力通常会在有数据时使用，或者
And this capability will often be used when data is present or
当需要进行某种计算或绘制某种图表时。
when some sort of calculation or some sort of plotting of a graph is needed.
在那种情况下，AI 可以生成一堆代码
In that case, the AI could generate a bunch of code
然后使用这个工具运行代码，以便为用户生成结果。
and then use this tool to run the code in order to generate a result for the user.
我们之前看到，推理模型可能会输入一个用户提示词，然后推理一会儿，
We saw previously how a reasoning model might input a user prompt, reason for a
同时利用上下文，并偶尔决定是否需要使用一个联网
while using the context and occasionally decide whether or not it needs to use a web
搜索工具来获取更多上下文。
search tool to get more context.
在这种情况下，它不仅可以选用联网搜索工具，
In this case, it has the option of not just using a web search tool,
还可以选用运行代码或代码执行工具，
but also a run-code or code execution tool in
AI 可以在其中编写基础计算机程序来分析数据。
which the AI can write a basic computer program to analyze data.
计算平均值、绘制图表，或做任何需要的事情，以得到最终答案。
Compute averages, plot a graph or whatever is needed in order to get to the final answer.
我们来看一个具体例子。
Let's look at a concrete example.
如果你经营一家珍珠奶茶店，
If you're running a bubble tea shop,
你可能想查看销售随时间变化的趋势，来回答类似这样的问题：
you may want to look at your sales trends over time to answer questions like,
你的新品饮品与现有饮品相比卖得好吗？
did your new drinks sell well compared to existing drinks?
如果你手头有销售数据，AI 可以帮你分析。
If you have sales data handy, AI can help you with this.
你可以把销售数据作为文件附加，并编写类似这样的提示词：
You can attach your sales data as a file and write a prompt like this one,
哪些饮品的销售变化最大？
which drinks had the biggest changes in sales?
把它画成图表。
Graph it.
然后 AI 会经历一个智能体式流程来分析和绘制数据。
The AI will then go through an agentic process to analyze the data and graph it.
检查数据，然后计算月度销售变化，
Inspect the data, then calculate the monthly changes in sales
并智能地分析你的数据，帮助你获得有用的洞察。
and do things like intelligently analyze your data to help you get useful insights.
例如，它可能会说：我注意到一些明显的模式。
For example, it may say things like, I'm noticing some clear patterns.
大多数饮品表现平稳，但有四款很突出。
Most drinks are flat, but four stand out.
现在为这四款绘制图表。
Now graph those.
所以它不只是绘制所有饮品的图表，
So not just graphing all the drinks,
而是识别出最有趣的饮品，并可能重点分析它们。
but identifying and potentially focusing on the most interesting ones.
然后它可能会生成像这样的一张图。横轴是时间，
Then it might generate a graph like this one. Time is on the horizontal axis
纵轴是销售数量，每款饮品用不同颜色绘制。
and number of sales on the vertical axis, with each drink graphed in its own color.
可以看出，草莓抹茶在春季销量大涨，
So the strawberry matcha took off in spring,
芒果绿茶和草莓柠檬水在夏季大涨，
mango green tea and strawberry lemonade in summer,
而你的新品椰子奶茶在秋季表现很好。
and your new coconut milk tea did well in fall.
它还添加了这些彩色高亮，使这些趋势更加突出。
It also added these colorful highlights to make these trends stand out.
所以只需几分钟，你就能得到一张像这样非常有用的图。
So in just a few minutes, you can get a highly useful graph like this.
从这张图中，你可能会得出结论：
From this graph, you might conclude
你为草莓抹茶做的春季促销效果很好，
that your spring promotion for Strawberry Matcha was strong,
也许明年你还想再做一次。
and maybe you want to try it again next year.
你可以继续迭代这张图，
You can keep going and iterate on this graph
并请求不同的洞察或对图表进行修改，或者提供更多关于
and ask for different insights or changes to the graph or give more context about
你业务的上下文，让 AI 更有机会发现更有用的洞察。
your business to the AI to give it a better shot at finding more useful insights.
但让我给你展示一个更需要长时间思考的例子。
But let me show you a more long-thinking example,
你可以把销售分析做得更进一步，要求生成一张更全面的图表。
you could take your sales analysis further and ask for a more comprehensive graphic.
例如，你可能想为你的业务制作一张年度回顾图，用来
For example, you might want to create a year in review graphic for your business to
展示给你的团队。
present to your team.
这需要用几种不同的方式分析你的所有数据，找出最
This involves analyzing all your data in a few different ways to find out what's most
值得分享的内容。
interesting to share.
所以你可能会写一个这样的提示词：创建一页年度回顾图，用于我们的
So you might write a prompt like create a 1-slide year in review graphic for our
珍珠奶茶店，仔细分析数据以获取洞察，
Bubble Tea Shop, analyze the data carefully for insights
然后再次附上你的数据文件。
and again attach your data file.
在提示词中使用“仔细”这样的词，可能会让 AI 思考好几分钟，
Using the words carefully in your prompt may trigger the AI to think for several
来完成这项分析。
minutes to complete this analysis
它可能会经历一个智能体式思考过程，就像你在上一页幻灯片中看到的那样。
and it might go through an agentic thinking process like you saw on the previous slide.
它很可能会编写并运行代码，来计算收入和售出商品数量等内容。
And it will likely write and run code to calculate things like revenue and items sold.
最后，你可能会得到一张像这样的图，包含许多有趣的洞察，
And in the end, you might get a graphic like this with a lot of interesting insights
比如黑糖和经典款是被点得最多的饮品，
like brown sugar and classic being the most ordered drinks
而且大多数顾客选择大杯。
and most customers choosing a large drink.
这张图还采用了有创意的珍珠奶茶配色方案。
This graphic also has a creative bubble tea color scheme.
你可能想要仔细核对这些数字，确保它们符合你的
You probably want to double-check these figures to make sure they match your
预期，因为 AI 有时会产生幻觉。
expectations since the AI sometimes can hallucinate.
但仅仅通过提示词，你就能在相对较短的时间内得到一份不错的分析。
But you can get a good analysis in a relatively short period of time just by prompting.
这份分析相当可能是准确的，因为 AI 是通过编写
That's fairly likely to be accurate since AI calculated these numbers by writing
并运行代码来计算这些数字的。
and running code.
我鼓励你自己尝试这类分析，
I encourage you to try this type of analysis yourself
如果你有销售数据或个人数据，并且想从中获取洞察的话。
if you have data like sales data or personal data you're interested in getting insights from.
如果你使用的 AI 模型可以运行代码，它什么时候会选择这样做？
If you're using an AI model that can run code, when would it choose to do so?
我们看到，对于某些问题，它可以使用预训练知识。
We're seeing that for some questions, it can use its pretrained knowledge.
如果你问的问题只需要用互联网上的常识来回答，
If you're asking for a question that can be answered using common knowledge on the
那它已经知道的内容可能就足够好了。
internet, what it already knows may well be good enough.
如果你问的是特定的实时问题，
If you're asking a specific question that is real time,
那么支持联网搜索的 AI 会帮你得到更好的答案。
then web search enabled AI will help you get a better answer.
你可能会想让它使用深度研究模式，
You may want to ask it to use deep research mode
如果你有一个更复杂的问题，可能需要多次相关搜索，
if you have a more complex question that may require multiple related searches,
比如为你的万圣节房屋制定一个完整计划，以及那些
such as to come up with a complete plan for your Halloween house and for queries
需要计算或起草的查询。
that require calculation or drafting.
这些类型的问题最可能让它编写
Those are the types of questions where it's most likely to write
并运行一些代码，以便为你精确地完成该任务。
and run some code in order to carry out that task precisely for you.
现在 AI 能做的最强大事情之一是编写
One of the most powerful things that AI can do now is write
并运行代码，以便为你执行任务。
and run code in order to carry out the task for you.
如果你有一些数据，想从中获得洞察，
If you have some data that you want to get insights from,
我鼓励你尝试用 AI 模型来探索这些数据。
I encourage you to try exploring it with an AI model.
AI 并不总是可靠，而且它更擅长简单分析，而不是非常复杂的分析。
AI isn't always reliable and is better at simple analysis than really complex ones.
所以请考虑再次检查这些结论，
So consider double checking these conclusions,
但这比你自己在 Excel 或 Google Sheets 中做分析要快得多。
but it can be much faster than having to do the analysis yourself in Excel or Google Sheets.
而且它在许多场合帮助我发现了数据中有用的洞察，为了将
And it has on many occasions helped me discover useful insights in my data to put
你的技能付诸实践，
your skills into practice.
我们为你准备了最后一个练习实验和一个可选的最终项目。
We have one last practice lab and an optional final project for you.
让我们进入下一个视频，看看这些是什么。
Let's go into the next video to see what these are.
我很期待你尝试用 AI 构建游戏和应用。
I'm excited for you to test out building games and applications using AI.
这应该能让你初步体验用 AI 可以构建什么。
This should give you a taste for what's possible to build with AI.
进入实验后，你可以阅读这里显示的说明。
When you get to the lab, you can read through these instructions shown here.
不过我现在先把它关掉，
But I'm just gonna dismiss this for now
然后我要点击用于烟花秀的提示词。
and I'm just going to click the prompt for a fireworks show.
我鼓励你仔细阅读这个提示词，这样
I encourage you to read through this prompt carefully so
你就能理解构建这样一个应用需要什么。
that you understand what it takes to build an app like this.
我只需点击运行，这个简短的提示词就会构建出这个应用。
And I'm just gonna hit run and this short prompt will build this application.
我确实没有指定很多细节，
I did leave a lot of things unspecified,
但看起来我的 AI 做出了合理的决定。
but it looks like my AI has made reasonable decisions.
如果我点击鼠标，它就会发射出非常漂亮的烟花。
And if I click my mouse, it launches pretty neat fireworks.
如果我不想自己来发射，
If I don't want to launch them by myself,
auto show 会运行我的自动烟花秀。然后是——
the auto show runs my automatic fireworks show. And then here's the.
压轴表演。
Grand finale.
非常酷。
So pretty cool.
一个很棒的功能是，你其实可以分享你构建的应用。
One neat feature is that you can actually share the apps you built.
所以我要点击分享，把链接复制到剪贴板，
So I'm gonna click share, just copy the link to my clipboard,
然后我可以用这个 URL 打开一个新标签页。
and I can open up a new tab with this URL.
这实际上会在我的网页浏览器中启动这个烟花应用。
And this actually launches the fireworks app in my web browser.
所以如果你把这个 URL 分享给朋友，
So if you share this URL with a friend,
他们就能运行你刚刚创建的这个烟花应用。
they'll be able to run the fireworks app that you just created.
构建简单应用最让我享受的一点是能够
One of the things I most enjoy about building simple applications is being able to
与朋友分享。
share with friends.
所以我鼓励你，或许可以把你构建的东西分享出去，
So I encourage you to maybe take whatever you built and consider sharing
分享给朋友，看看他们有什么想法。
that with friends and see what they think.
你可以随意使用 Firework Show 这个提示词，
Feel free to take the Firework Show prompt,
修改它，看看你能否得到不同的结果，
modify it and see if you can get a different result
一个可能更让你喜欢的结果。
that could be even more to your liking.
第二个例子，让我点击这个配色方案提示词。
Second example, let me click on the color palette prompt.
如果你在设计一个网站，
If you are designing a website,
你可能需要做的一件事就是为网站选择一个配色方案。
something you may have to do is choose a color palette for the website.
所以使用这样的提示词，你就可以构建一个配色方案选择器。
And so with a prompt like this, you can build a color palette picker.
它有一个用 RGB 值表示的基础颜色。
It has a base color in RGB values.
这个颜色实际上大致就是我衬衫的颜色。
So this is actually roughly the color of my shirt.
你可以选择互补色、相似色等等配色方案，
And you can choose complementary, analogous, and so on, color palettes that,
你知道，它们搭配起来真的很不错。希望你玩得开心。
you know, they actually go pretty well together. Hope you have fun playing with this.
所以我希望你能尝试所有四个内置提示词，另外，
So I hope you try out all four of these built-in prompts and additionally,
请试着用你自己的提示词。
try using your own prompt.
例如，这里我会让它构建一个闪卡应用来帮我练习
For example, here I'm going to ask it to build a flashcard app to help me practice
基础法语词汇。
basic French vocabulary.
这个过程可能需要几秒钟，完成后你可能会得到这样的结果。
This process may take a few seconds, and when it's done, this is what you might get.
等等，是什么？对，还不错什么的。看来我答对了。
Wait, what is? Yes, not too shabby and so on. Looks like I got that right.
看起来它把所有的答案都显示在右边了。
It looks like it's giving me all the answers here on the right.
但如果我不想要这样，我可以回去
But if I don't want that, I can go back
修改提示词来重新设计我的闪卡应用。
and modify the prompt to redesign my flashcard app.
请尽情尝试。
Please have fun with this.
我觉得很受启发，仅凭一句英文提示词，
And I find it inspiring that with just one English prompt,
你就能构建一个网页，进而构建像这样的应用。
you can build a web page to build applications like these.
最终项目是基于一个主题的研究来构建一个简单的应用
The final project is to build a simple app from research on a topic
你感兴趣的主题。
that interests you.
我们将经历三个步骤。首先，头脑风暴一个研究问题，
We're going to go through three steps. first, brainstorm a research question,
然后开展研究，再构建一个应用。
then run research, and then build an app.
我鼓励你仔细阅读这些说明，
I encourage you to read through these instructions,
但在这个演示中我会先跳过它们。
but I'm just going to dismiss them for this demo.
第一步是头脑风暴一个研究问题，主题可以是你想探索的
The first step is to brainstorm a research question on either a topic you want to
或你想做的决定，
explore or a decision you want to make,
比如研究保健品、买车、与职业相关的事情，或
like researching health supplements or buying a car or things to do with your career or
一些有趣的天文学内容。
some fun things of astronomy.
我选择职业相关的这个提示，你也可以选择其他提示。
Let me pick the careers one given this prompt or some other one that you may choose.
我会鼓励你接着给 AI 更多背景信息，
I would encourage you to then give the AI more context,
所以我提到探索不同职业。
so I mentioned exploring different careers.
了解我、我的情况。
Know about me, my situation.
假设我在大学学习深度学习。我想在办公室工作。
Let's say I'm at university studying deep learning. I want to work in an office.
我鼓励你比我这个演示中写的更多。
And I encourage you to write more than I am here in this demo walkthrough.
但让我把它发给 AI，这里它会帮助我头脑风暴出几个具体的
But let me send it to the AI, and here it will help me to brainstorm a few specific
研究问题，比如有哪些职业？
research questions, such as what careers?
能让我花很多时间协作，日常又是什么样？
Let me spend a lot of time collaborating and what does it look like day to day?
希望你选择一些与你生活相关的内容
So hopefully you pick something that's relevant to your life
这会帮助你头脑风暴出一系列不同的问题
and this will help you brainstorm a range of different questions
希望这些问题会让你感兴趣。
that hopefully will be interesting to you.
我们还有一个 AI 导师，呃，
And we also have an AI mentor, uh,
就头脑风暴的过程进展给你一些反馈。
to give you some feedback on how the brainstorming process is going.
因此在这个头脑风暴工作流程中，
So in this brainstorming workflow,
我会通读这些问题并给出反馈。
I would read through these questions and give feedback.
比如我最感兴趣的是问题 1，
So let's say I'm most interested in question 1,
但喜欢问题 3 的具体性，嗯，
but like the specificity of question 3, um,
还想确保我有时间去上班。
also want to make sure I have time to go to my job.
通过这类反馈，AI 现在有了额外的背景信息，了解什么才是一个
So this type of feedback, the AI now has additional context about what makes an
对你来说有趣的研究问题。
interesting research question for you.
于是它会将其优化为稍好一些的选项。
And so it refines it to slightly better options.
让我们再来一轮。
Let's take one more turn.
基于这三个问题，我的反馈是，
Based on these three questions, my feedback is,
我还想确保考虑非营利领域的工作。
and I also want to make sure to consider nonprofit work.
因此，通过几轮查看头脑风暴出的研究问题
And so by going a few rounds with looking at the brainstorm research questions
并给出反馈，我们现在已将其精炼为少数几个研究问题。
and giving feedback, we've now refined it to a handful of research questions.
所以，如果你在用 LLM，你其实可以多轮要求它优化
So if you're using an LLM, you can actually go for multiple rounds asking to refine
这些问题，把它们合并。
the questions, combine them.
但让我先到此为止，暂停练习，然后说，
But let me just end this, pause the exercise for now and say,
我最喜欢这个问题，
I'd like this question the best,
我会选这个问题进入第 2 步，
and I'm just going to pick this question to go on to step 2,
既然我已经制定了一个研究问题。
now that I've formulated a research question.
我们刚刚完成的就是一次头脑风暴练习
And what we just did was go through a brainstorming exercise
这展示了你可以如何与 AI 反复互动，来头脑风暴其他
that's an example of how you may iterate with your AI to brainstorm any of the other
可能的主题，而不仅仅是确定一个要研究的问题。
possible topics as well, not just to identify a research question to work on.
既然我已经选好了研究问题，让我再给它一些背景信息。
Now that I've picked my research question, let me give it a little bit more context.
我还想了解薪资和典型薪酬。
So I also want to know about salaries and typical compensation.
我想用这些来源，比如论坛上的个人经验等等。
And I wanted to use these sources, forums for personal experience and so on.
我鼓励你加入更多个人背景信息，并提供更多来源
I'd encourage you to add more personal context and add more sources
比我这次快速演示中做得更多。
than I'm doing in this quick run through.
不过我们先让它完成这项研究，让它接着去做吧。
But let's just have it carry out this research and let's have it go ahead and do so.
AI mentor 对我的提示给了一些反馈，运行了一会儿之后，
The AI mentor gives some feedback on my prompts and after running for a while here,
我的联网搜索 AI。
my web search enabled AI.
这里有一组相当不错的结果，为第三步也是最后一步提供了大量引用。
Here's a pretty decent set of results with lots of citations for the third and final step.
拿到研究报告后，我们接着来构建一个应用。
After you've gotten your research report, let's go build an app.
我们可以根据这些报告构建一个测验来测试我的知识。
We can build a quiz to test my knowledge based on the reports.
或者做一个小游戏，或者生成信息图。
Or there's a mini game or build the infographic.
这三个其实都很有趣，不过我选择测验这个选项。
All three of these are actually pretty fun, but I'm gonna choose the quiz option.
那么我在这里要构建一个包含五道题的多项选择测验
So here I'm gonna build a five question multiple choice quiz
我们在第二步创建的研究报告已上传到这里
and the research report that we had created from Step 2 is uploaded here
作为附件，以便提供更多上下文。
as an attachment to give it more context.
为了让结果更可预测，在我们的网站上，
And to keep the results more predictable, in our website,
这个提示词被置灰，因此不可编辑。
this prompt is grayed out so it's not editable.
但你随时可以把报告复制到第三方 AI 系统中，比如
But you can always copy the report into a third party AI system such
ChatGPT、Gemini 或 Claude，以便进行更多尝试。
as ChatGPT or Gemini or Claude to experiment more.
我鼓励你体验所有这些。它们其实都很有趣。
And I encourage you to play all of these. All of these are actually pretty fun.
不过让我直接生成我的测验应用吧。
But let me just generate my quiz app.
这同样需要花一点时间。
So that will again take a little bit of time.
这就是生成的应用。
And so here's the app.
让我选这个。
Let me pick that.
是的，看来我答对了。
Yep, looks like I got that right.
以此类推。
And so on.
和之前一样，你可以使用分享按钮复制这个链接
And same as before, you can copy this link using the share button
并把这个应用分享给你的朋友，看看他们是否喜欢。
and share this app with your friends and see if they like it.
所以我希望你享受这个迭代式头脑风暴流程，
So I hope you enjoy going through the iterative brainstorming workflow,
这是使用 AI 时非常有用的技能。
which is a very useful skill to have when using AI.
然后为它提供足够的上下文，让它为你做研究
And then provide enough context for it to do research for you
然后基于或受这项研究启发，
and then based on or inspired by that research,
构建我们刚刚展示的那些有趣应用之一
build one of the fun apps that we just showed you
甚至可以分享给一些朋友。
and maybe even share with some friends.
我希望你享受探索这个实验和可选最终项目，
I hope you enjoy exploring the lab and the optional final project,
我也希望你能与他人分享你的最终项目。
and I hope you'll share your final projects with others as well.
再说一次，如果你有兴趣进一步学习，
And again, if you're interested in learning more,
我鼓励你参加 Build with Andrew 课程。
I encourage you to take the Build with Andrew course.
完成后，我们最后一个视频见。
Once you're done, I'll see you in one final video.
恭喜你完成本课程，掌握了所有技巧
Congratulations on making it to the end of this course with all the techniques
你现在已经准备好成为一名 AI 高效使用者。
you've learned, you're now ready to be an AI power user.
我希望你在个人生活和工作中找到许多场景，
I hope you find a lot of places in your personal life and work
让你的技能为你带来益处，
where your skills will benefit you,
比如用 AI 帮助头脑风暴，或使用深度研究
like using AI to help brainstorm or use deep research
当你需要详尽研究报告时，或用 AI 帮助你写作
where you need thoroughly researched reports or use AI to help you with writing
甚至生成多模态输出和代码。
and even generate multimodal outputs and code.
即使在你做这些的同时，AI 模型也会不断进步。
And even as you're doing all this, AI models will keep on getting better.
所以请持续尝试新模型，给 AI 布置困难任务，
So please keep trying new models and give AI hard tasks
并提供高质量的上下文。
and provide high quality context.
这会帮助你不断打磨对 AI 能做什么和不能做什么的直觉。
This will help you to keep honing your intuitions about what AI can and cannot do.
我相信你会从这项极其强大的技术中收获很多。
I'm confident you get a lot out of this incredibly powerful technology.
感谢你坚持陪我走到这里。
Thank you for sticking with me to this point.
我希望你运用这些能力来帮助自己、你的朋友、
And I hope you use these powers to help yourself, your friends,
你的社区，并去为自己和他人创造一个更美好的世界。
your community and go make the world a better place for yourself and others.